<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of vvarre, or The image of martiall discipline contayning many vsefull directions for musters &amp; armes, and the very first principles in discipline, the ground postures, all the military motions now vsed ... By Edvvard Cooke.</title>
            <author>Cooke, Edward, fl. 1626-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844311</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9112</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9112)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1169:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of vvarre, or The image of martiall discipline contayning many vsefull directions for musters &amp; armes, and the very first principles in discipline, the ground postures, all the military motions now vsed ... By Edvvard Cooke.</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Edward, fl. 1626-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Purfoot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ [par.]²  B-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF WARRE, OR <hi>The Image of Martiall Diſcipline: contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> many vſefull directions for Muſters &amp; Armes, and the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry firſt principles in Diſcipline, the groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>es, all the Military motions now vſed: Their vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtration of their vſe, firſt by precept, then by example, Shewing how to doe them, how to performe them gracefully, how to command them properly, playnely, without diſtractions to the Souldiers. Contayning many excellent Pollicies and Stratagemes, many good Documents for young Souldiers, ſhewing how they muſt bee qualified, what qualities beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits them.</p>
            <p>A worke fitt for all Noble, Generous and good Spirits, that loue Honour, or Honourable Action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDVVARD COOKE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exodus. 15.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is a man of Warre: his Name is <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Tho: Purfoot.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable and moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Sackuile,</hi> Baron of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurst</hi> Earle of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and Knight of the Noble order of the Garter</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that write vpon any ſerious Subiect (right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and moſt noble Lord) whether it be of Peace or Warre, commonly doe dedicate their Bookes to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons: to the end, that what they haue ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by Labour and Study, may by their greatneſſe be protected from Maledictions and Enuie: and they choſe ſuch, whoſe eminent vertues (exempt from Riualles) is of all admired, by all obſerued, and withall beloued, where the choycest witts ſhelter their chiefeſt workes. Hence I take my imitation, and in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie proſtrate this my poore labour to kiſse your noble hands, not as any adition to your vncontrolable and approued knowledge, but as a weake Fabricke which onely wanteth the ſupport of your much admired goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>In former time, if any were longheaded, as <hi>Pericles,</hi> crooked no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as <hi>Cyrus,</hi> foretopped with his hayre growing vpright as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander;</hi> he had fauour ſhewed in all Courts, and in euery company he came in: Such reſpect did they giue to their outward ſhapes, who it may be had not any of their Habituall vertues; Oh then what loue, what reſpect ought euery one (in what degree or place ſoeuer) to giue you, that haue the Habit of their vertues, onely want their blemiſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pericles</hi> loue to his Country. <hi>Cyrus</hi> (the elders) care of his Souldiers. <hi>Alexanders</hi> vertues (not vices) are pregnant in your honour, the world ſees it. <hi>Demetrius, Nero,</hi> and <hi>Caligula,</hi> (not ſetting their Empire aſide) are not to be compared with your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: yet let me lay Gold to copper, that the gold may appeare the more glorious.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Demetrius</hi> care was more for an Aſtrologicall Cloake (thereby to hang the world on his backe,) then for his Kingdome or people. But your honours care is for the Kingdome, to doe good to euery member thereof, Mentally, Actually, to your power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nero</hi> the Tyrants care was for new inuented Garments (dayly) to weare none twice: your care is that euery man haue good Armes to grace the Kingdome dayly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caligulas</hi> care was to weare <hi>Sacras Deorum veſtes,</hi> to ſet forth the greatneſſe of his authority. But your care is the Habit of a Souldier, ſhewing power in your command that all may obey.</p>
            <p>Theſe Noble parts being eminent in your honour, are powerfull inducments for me to ſue euer for ſuch a Noble Patrone, therefore to you, and onely to your honoured ſelfe, I humbly dedicate this Booke. The Booke deſerues more your honours cenſure then prayſe; for like <hi>Phormio</hi> it ſeemes to reade a Lecture of warre (to an <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi>) who for it was reproued, but if I eſcape from your honour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chekt, I will impute it (not to deſert in me) but to your honours ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, vſuall Mildneſſe, paſsing by my preſumption. Thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting the Booke to your Noble patronage, you to the Almighties protection, and my ſelfe to your honours command and ſeruice, I euer rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In Field and out of Field your honours Seruant EDVVARD COOKE,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:3"/>
            <head>To Captaine <hi>Pert,</hi> Lieuetenant <hi>Millen,</hi> Lieuetenant <hi>Keneſton,</hi> Ancient Gualter, Ancient <hi>Clarke,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Tho: Webſter,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Foſter</hi> Gentlemen, and to all the reſt of their place and office, in the Sixe Cautionarie, or trayned bandes of <hi>Middleſex.</hi> ALSO, To the worthy Captayne <hi>Goſtock</hi> Muſtermaiſter for the County of <hi>Middleſex:</hi> And to all the ſuruiuing Founders of the <hi>Artillery Garden,</hi> and <hi>Military yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Actions of vertue (worthy Gentlemen and Souldiers) ſhould ſo much affect the beholders, that they ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently not onely admire them, but indeauour to follow them.<note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeaſar.</note> 
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> reading the braue acts of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great fell (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) a weeping, and was angry with himſelfe, to thinke how <hi>Alexander</hi> a young man (iuſt about his age) had notwithſtanding conquered the whole world, whereas he as yet had done nothing worthy the name of a Generall: From this Princely Emulation he fell to Action, and became ſo excellent, that <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> himſelfe paralells him onely with <hi>Alexander.</hi> I make no doubt, but that ſetting before your eyes the braue exployts of your Anceſtors you haue beene mooued to practize Armes, by which you haue gayned great applauſe, (and worthy of it) becauſe you haue done good ſeruice to your King and Country.</p>
            <p>The greateſt ſeruice that men can doe, is to ſaue their Country frem dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The <hi>Romans</hi> gaue him a crowne that ſaued one Cittyzen: then how many crownes deſerueth you, that helpeth to ſaue a number.</p>
            <p>They vſed to make a Coyne for his commendation with this inſcription: <hi>The Senate and people of Rome for Citizens ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſaue the liues of men by teaching them the right vſe of their Armes, whereby they ſaue themſelues from danger. Would to God that all would follow you, as you doe follow the vertues and Actions of the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Grecians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecians</hi> were the firſt, that out of varietie of actions and long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience reduced the knowledge of Armes into an Art, and gaue precepts
<pb facs="tcp:9112:4"/> for the orderly mouing of a battaile, and taught, that the moments of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reſted not in the hands of multitudes, but in a few men rightly inſtructed to mannage Armes, and trayned vp in the obſeruation of the dicipline of the field. In which regard they had Schooles and Schoole-maiſters called <hi>Tac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> which deliuered the Art Militarie to ſuch as were deſirous to learne. Out of whoſe Schooles iſſued thoſe chiefs of Warre in number ſo many,<note place="margin">Captayne Bingham.</note> in Skill ſo exquiſite, in Vallor ſo peereleſſe, in all vertues beſeeming great Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls ſo admirable, that no Nation of <hi>Europe</hi> euen to this day hath been able to match, much leſſe to ouer-match their ſame and glory. The braue <hi>Romans</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> farre ſhort of them: yet the <hi>Romans</hi> following their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances both haue kept in vſe, and alſo ſet forth in writing the rules of Martiall policie or diſcipline: And you haue Schooles wherein you teach this Martiall policy or diſcipline to ſuch as are deſirous to learne. The one is called the <hi>Artillery garden,</hi> the other the <hi>Millitary-yard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe was erected by the Vertuous Gentlemen of <hi>London.</hi> The ſecond by you the no leſſe vertuous Gentlemen of <hi>Midleſex:</hi> out of theſe two Schooles as out of the former, haue iſſued men of worth taking their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: As Captaynes, Lieuetenants, Antients, and Sergeants, ſo that all the trayned bands in <hi>London</hi> &amp; <hi>Midleſex,</hi> are furniſhed with able &amp; ſufficient Officers out of both theſe Schooles, to your honours that were the Founders.</p>
            <p>I, the laſt in degree (of inferior officers) had my firſt egreſſe from the <hi>Artillery Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Schoole I ſpent Foure yeares compleat, to gayne the little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which I haue, neuer preſuming to ſhew my skill, much leſſe to contend with others in it: vntill the Scollers of another Schoole (Low-Country-like) banded together for tryall of skill, vrged me thereunto. Then for the honour of my Schoole (put on by my owne Schoole fellowes) I entred the Liſt to play my Schollers Prize: And I haue now done it, but whether I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it ill or well, reſteth not in me the Scholler to iudge but in you the Maiſters of Science, moſt skilfull in the Art Military. Iudge then and Cenſure,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend</hi> Edward Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:4"/>
            <head>To the worthy Company and whole body of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Souldiers, ſeruing in the Fift Cautionarie or Trayned Band of <hi>Midleſex,</hi> otherwiſe called Captayne <hi>Perts</hi> Company.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here a generall voyce warrants an approbation (worthie Gentlemen and Souldiers) there euery ſeruice is a Duty. The truth of it concernes &amp; inuites mee to write a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Epiſtle vnto you, and therein to extoll your worth: And none will diſcommend me for it, that either imitates your vertues, or would be prayſed (as you) for worth. Your worth Implyes your rare parts: your rare part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (though many) may bee Epitomized in Foure.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Your proneſſe of mind to beare Armes. <hi>2.</hi> Your actiueneſſe in all Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motions. <hi>3.</hi> Your Subiugated wills to obey your Officers. <hi>4.</hi> Your Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and Pythian like affection one to another.</p>
            <p>The three firſt are rare, but the fourth and laſt is the moſt rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent; For as a Diamond fairely ſet in Gold, it giues luſter to all the reſt, and makes me ſtile you <hi>Philonida</hi> or <hi>Philonis,</hi> a bande of friends, or true friendſhip, or indeed the <hi>Holy band.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> telleth of an holy band errected by one <hi>Gorgidas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Pelopidas.</note> which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of three Hundred choſen men, entertayned by the ſtate, &amp; kept within the Caſtle of <hi>Cadmea,</hi> called the Townes band, (as you the Kinges band:) This band was neuer broken nor ouerthrowne before the battaile of <hi>Chae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronea,</hi> where they were all ſlaine, found lincked together with cordes of ſilke arme in arme, Pikes ſticking in their breſts.<note place="margin">Philip King of Macedon. Father to Alexander the great.</note> King <hi>Philip</hi> their enemie ſhedding teares for them, and cauſing them to bee buried together, who in death would not be parted.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus the louing Holy Band,</l>
               <l>Fell by the <hi>Macedonians</hi> hand.</l>
               <l>Each one dying for his Frend,</l>
               <l>Keeping Friendſhip to the end.</l>
               <l>From whoſe aſhes doth ariſe,</l>
               <l>You that them doth Sympathize.</l>
               <l>Neuer to diſſolue together,</l>
               <l>Nor like God to liue for euer,</l>
               <l>For one by one, be ſure to die,</l>
               <l>Time takes away, time will ſupply.</l>
               <l>And as he brought you to the Wombe,</l>
               <l>So backe hee leads you to your Tombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in life and death, <hi>Edward Cooke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:5"/>
            <head>To his Brother in Law <hi>Thomas Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> a louer of Armes, and an expert Souldier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I firſt made entrance into this worke (you know wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Brother) that there was no ſpeech made in the Citty or Subburbes, of Plague or Pestilenc: But when I had almoſt finiſhed it, the Plague began amongest vs. Then was both ſpeech &amp; complaint too in an vnceſſant manner? So I leaſt of. In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ited by you in the heate thereof to finiſh it, (least dying and leauing it an abhortiue, it ſhould vtterly fayle and come to ruine.) But what auailed it mee to write of warlike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tratagemes and Policies, to oppoſe, opugne, repell an humaine Enemie in the field? when tht Lord God of Hosts great in pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, (whom none could reſiſt) was entred the field, deſtroying Thouſands on his right hand, Ten Thouſand on his left hand, and all the Kingdome in generall, had not his mercy exceeded his Ivstice.</p>
            <p>Then it was for mee not to write, but to pray: not to forcaſt where to flie from the ſword of the Lord, but how to ſubmit my ſelfe to the ſword of the Lord, which when the Lord ſaw, he manifeſted his power to me, preſeruing me, that I might hereafter truſt in him, and declare his goodneſſe to the Sonnes of men.</p>
            <p>Thus the Preſſe of the Lord went forth, it tooke away whole families; it contynued many Moneths together in the Subburb in be Citty.</p>
            <p>The Citty was almoſt deſolate (yet not deſolate) becauſe ſhe had a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God with a fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ming ſword, purging, not conſuming her? A bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour interceding for mercy not Iuſtice: A King on earth (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) weeping and praying in ſecret for her; calling vpon his Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirituall and Temporall, on all the Moyſeſes, and Arons in the Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me to ioyne with him in Prayer (as they had in faſting) &amp; to crye mightily vnto the Lord, <hi>to ſpare this Citty, the holy Citty, the Citty where his name was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay ſhee had a carefull Magiſtrate in her, whom diuine prouidence did preordayne to that place to do h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r good,<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r John Gore was then Lord Mayor of London. And Alderman Heylyne, and Alderman Parkebuſt, were Shriefes.</note> who went in perſon to viſite her, relei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her relinquiſhed members readie to ſtarue for want of foode: Sending his two worſhipfull Brothers the Shrieues to doe it for him, if his Lordſhip was otherwaies imployed.</p>
            <p>Theſe two good Samaritans came into the Suburbes among the poore Trino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantes of Saint Sepulchers, inquiring their number, their eſtate, their wants, their greiuances, finding them great (paſt their expectation) they re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turned
<pb facs="tcp:9112:5"/> with melting hearts, condoling their miſerie, and informing the Lord Mayor of it, who by them (&amp; through their meanes) ſent inſtantly a ſupply of Fourteene Poundes for their reliefe: commanding information weekely to be giuen of their wants, &amp; they ſhould be relieued. Which was done by me, and performed by them, euen till the ſickneſſe was mightily decreaſed, &amp; our Gentlemen returned home, ſo they left off: being ſeconded by M. <hi>George Allington</hi> Eſquier, (and one of the Maiſters of the <hi>Pipe</hi> office) who ſent them Fortie ſhillinges, as formerly he had done at other times weekely. This money was truly distributed, though it came not to my hands: The money that came to my handes (from the Lord Mayor, Sheriffes, and Churchwardens) was Twenty Fiue Poundes Ten ſhillinges. So when all this was diſcharged, and the plague quite ceaſed, and thankes rendered to Almighty God for our deliuerance: I betooke my ſelfe to Penn and Paper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to fininſh what before I vndertooke; which by Gods helpe I haue ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; and would not haue publiſhed it to the world, had not ſome Low Country-like forced, You brotherlike perſwaded; Now if any good come thereby, let ſuch as reape it thanke you, who would not let me reſt till I had finiſhed, then printed it: If none at all, then let them blame me, not you, if not, excuſe me thus: he had a good intention, but hee failed of the execution, in this I reſt: and reſting rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your louing Brother,</hi> Edward Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:6"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The Index or Table, briefely poynting</hi> out the ſeuerall Contents of euery perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Chapter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of Armes and Men: And of the choiſe of Men for Souldiers Chap. 1.</item>
               <item>Out of what Clymate or place Souldiers may be moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyently taken: Chap: 2.</item>
               <item>Of what Age Souldiers ſhould be allowed, either for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeruice or Muſter. Chap: 3</item>
               <item>How they muſt be armed. Chap: 4.</item>
               <item>What Exerciſes they muſt vſe when they want Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Chap. 5: <hi>viz.</hi> Running, Leaping, Vaulting, and Swymminge.</item>
               <item>Why Souldiers muſt vſe Runninge. Chap: 6.</item>
               <item>Why Souldiers muſt vſe Leapinge. Chap. 7.</item>
               <item>Why Souldiers muſt vſe Vaultinge. Chap. 8.</item>
               <item>Why Souldiers muſt vſe Swimminge. Chap. 9.</item>
               <item>Vnto what younge Souldiers muſt be diſciplyned and how often trayned in a Moneth. Chap: 10</item>
               <item>When Souldiers muſt be brought into the fieild for Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. Chap. 11.</item>
               <item>What the beats of the drumme are, which Souldiers muſt Know. Chap. 12</item>
               <item>What the diſtances in fiiles and Rankes are which Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers muſt know. Chap. 13.</item>
               <item>How a fiile and a Ranke is diſtinguiſhed for a Souldier to know. Chap. 14</item>
               <item>What the fiights are which Souldiers muſt be expert in. Chap. 15</item>
               <item>What the qualities are which befitt Martiall Men. Chapter. 16.</item>
               <item>Of wiſdome and pollicie: The vſe of it: how it may be
<pb facs="tcp:9112:6"/> attained: with a breife Summary of Stratagems and polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes pertynent for theſe tymes. Chap. 17</item>
               <item>Of the vſe of Faceinge. Chap. 18</item>
               <item>The words of Command for it. Chap. 19</item>
               <item>Of the vſe of wheeling. Chap: 20</item>
               <item>The words of Commande for it. Chap 21.</item>
               <item>Of the vſe of Countermarch and the words of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande for it. Chap. 22</item>
               <item>Of the vſe of doublinge. Chap. 23.</item>
               <item>Of the diſtances to be obſerued in Battaile, Of their vſe, and how to be Commanded. Chap 24.</item>
               <item>The words of Commande by which the length or depth of a Battaile, may be doubled in place or number. Chap. 25.</item>
               <item>A platforme of Exerciſing for thoſe that would; but are not exquiſite. Chap. 26.</item>
               <item>The Poſtures of the Musket in that forme, as it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnto vs by his Maieſtie, and his moſt honorable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Counſell. Chap. 27</item>
               <item>The ſeuerall Poſtures of the Pike, abſtracted from that Booke which the Prince of Orange his Excellencie did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe of. Chap. 28.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:7"/>
            <head>Chapter the firſt. OF ARMES AND MEN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ARRE is my Subiect, and therefore my firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhall be of Armes and Men; becauſe in them conſiſteth whatſoeuer belongeth or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayneth to Warre, that is vnto Land ſeruice As <hi>Cato</hi> (the ſinguler and notable Author a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Latines</hi>) doth teſtifie.<note place="margin">Marcus Cato.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant of <hi>Vegetius</hi> definition:<note place="margin">Vegetius Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Chop. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, that whatſoeuer appertayneth to Warre, is diuided into three parts: Horſemen, Footmen, and Navies. Horſemen to keepe the playnes, Footmen to keepe the Hilles, Citties, Champion ground, and alſo ſteepe places: Navies to keepe the Seas and waters: But <hi>Vegetius</hi> implyes herein both Land and Sea ſeruice; I onely (here) but Land ſeruice.</p>
            <p>With Sea ſeruice I will not intermedle, with Land ſeruice (by Gods helpe I will) and ſo I begin with Armes.</p>
            <p>Armes doth vphold Kingdomes, States, and Lawes;<note place="margin">Of Ames.</note> The firſt thought therefore of a Prince or State, that is reſolued to put an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into the field, ought to prouide Armes.</p>
            <p>Armes are the ſecurity of their owne Soldiers, the terror of the Enemie, the aſſured and ordinary meanes of Victory.</p>
            <p>The antiquitie of Armes is all one with the beginnig of Warre. For when of ancient times mighty men puffed with Pride, and led by Ambition,<note place="margin">Captaine Bing ham in his notes vpon Aelia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſought to bring vnder ſubiection their bordering Neighbours, they were forced to fly to the inuention of Armes, without which no victorie could be obtayned. Since Armes haue been taken vp for defence alſo, Neceſſity the mother of Arts, inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away to withſtand Ambition.</p>
            <p>Now Armes are Implicitly taken for <hi>Headpeeces, Gorgets, Curaces, Vambraces, Gauntlets, Taces, Swords, Pikes, Muskets, Hargabuſes, Petronells, Piſtolls, Frontlets,</hi> and <hi>Pectoralls</hi> for horſes; with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:9112:8"/> neceſſaries appertayning and going vnder the name of defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and offenciue Armes.</p>
            <p>Of theſe a Prince or State ought to haue ſtore. For warlike Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and victorius haue euer ſought to haue aduantage of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies by aduantage of Armes.</p>
            <p>This our Nation knowes to be true, and therefore by continuall ſuply of of Armes they make way for new victories.</p>
            <p>The next care of a Prince or State, is to prouide Men.</p>
            <p>All men are not fit for warre, therefore there muſt be a choyſe of Men.</p>
            <p>This is likewiſe premeditated vpon in the thoughts of a Prince or State before they vndertake Warre: As is apparant by the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Romanes,</hi> who had their Muſter Maſters for the choyſe of their men, &amp; their <hi>Tribunes</hi> &amp; <hi>Centurions</hi> to make them Souldiers. Theſe taught their young ſoldiers the vſe of all their Armes, and were preſent at their exerciſes;</p>
            <p>Making them runne, leape, vault, ſhoot, caſt darts, fling ſtones of a pound weight, foyne and thruſt with the ſword, &amp; not to ſtrike downe wright: Such as were expert, they rewarded, preferring them to places of deſert, giuing them wheaten bread, (the vnexpert) bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread, keeping them from preferment vntill they could do ſome thing as well as the beſt: Then they were preferred as Souldiers for a Legion. This did the <hi>Romanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Care then ought to be had (you ſee) in the choyſe of men and Armes.</p>
            <p>The burthen of which care doth reſt on the diſcreet and honeſt Muſter-maiſter, whom the Prince or State for ſome good cauſe doth repoſe their truſt in. And therefore all his wits muſt bee ſet on worke for this ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> But there may a queſtion ariſe, whether a Muſter maſter ſhould chuſe more for ſtature or ſtrength.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, ſtaturo and ſtrength are both ſeruiceable, but curage ioyned to them is more auailable: Therefore currage is more to be regarded then ſtature.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vegetius</hi> Lib. 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</note>
               <hi>Marius</hi> (I confeſſe) being Conſull of <hi>Rome</hi> alwaies choſe yong Souldiers of tall ſtature, ſo that he would allow none for horſemen in the wings or front of his Battaile, but ſuch as were Sixe foot high, or fiue and tenne inches at the leaſt.</p>
            <p>But then there was (ſaith <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi>) mor plenty of people, and
<pb facs="tcp:9112:8"/> more that followed the Warres.</p>
            <p>And now the Philoſepher (with his ſaying) is iuſtified: <hi>The longer the world doth continue, the leſſer bodies it will produce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let Muſter-maiſters doe as they may, and rather chuſe for ſtrength then ſtature.</p>
            <p>And that they are not herein deceiued, they haue <hi>Homer</hi> for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who declareth that <hi>Tideus</hi> was but ſmall of ſtature, but yet of good courage and ſtomach.</p>
            <p>Then more requiſite it is that Souldiers ſhould be ſtrong and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lient then huge and great.</p>
            <p>If that all our Muſter-maiſters would chuſe thus, what ſtrong, valiant Souldiers ſhould our State haue. But either through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, or to curry fauour, or for want of knowledge, they doe that as they may be aſhamed of: But to take away all excuſes of want of knowledge, I will out of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi> ſhew them how they ſhould chuſe them.</p>
            <p>Let the young man therefore that ſhall bee a Souldier not looke drowſely, let him be ſtraight necked, broad breaſted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius.</hi> lib. 1 <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</note> let his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders bewell fleſhed, let him haue ſtrong fingers, long armes, a gaunt bellie, ſlender legges, the calfe and the feet not to full of fleſh, but knit faſt with hard and ſtrong ſinewes: Finding theſe tokens in a Souldier he may proue good.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Pirhus</hi> would often ſay to his Muſter-maiſters, chuſe you good bodies, and I will make them good Souldiers.</p>
            <p>But well, ſay he haue all theſe? and yet be of no occupation or ſcience, ſhall wee chuſe him (may they ſay) why not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vegetius</hi> (I confeſſe) would haue none to bee called to the warres but Smithes, Carpenters, Butchers, Hunters of the Hart and the wild Boares: excluding from the Campe, all Fiſhers, Fowlers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturers, Lynnen weauers, and whoſoeuer that dealeth with any thing that belongeth to womaniſh niceneſſe.</p>
            <p>But what is Trade to man-hood; yet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi> Iudgement is ſound: For what men are more beneficial to a Campe, then Smithes, Carpenters and the like.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Romane</hi> Legion being as a well furniſhed Citty ſtored with all kindes of Artificers: The ſtrength of that Realme (and to ſay truth) the name of the Romans laie in this choyſe.</p>
            <p>Their many diſcomfeictures &amp; damages by the enemie (<hi>Vegetius</hi> imputes) to their careleſſe neglect of thoſe men, and is bold to tell
<pb facs="tcp:9112:9"/> the Emperour <hi>Valentinian</hi> in playne words,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That neuer ſped that Army well in battell, whereof hee that tooke the muſter was any whit negligent in allowing the Souldiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I forbeare to ſpeake more for feare of giuing offence, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede forward to the next Chapter, to ſhew out of what Clymate, Place, Citty, or Country, young Souldiers ſhould be choſen, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken moſt conueniently.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Out of what Clymate, Place, Citty or Country, young ſouldiers ſhould be choſen or taken moſt conueniently.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As Vegetius notes Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>THe temperatnes of the Clymate (ſayth the learned) doth very much auaile, not onely to ſtrengthen the body, but alſo the mind: and therefore they are of oppinion that thoſe people that are fartheſt off from the parching power of the Sunne are for their temperature the beſt of all to make Souldiers: for ſay they, thoſe Nations which bee nigh to the Sunne, parched and dried with ouer much heate, haue more wit indeede, but yet leſſe blood within them. And for this cauſe they dare not manfully and boldly ſtand vnto it when they fight, well knowing how little blood they haue, and feare much therefore wounding: Contrariwiſe, the people of the North whom the Sunne burneth not ſo neere, being more raſh and vnaduiſed, yet a great deale better blouded, are moſt readie of all and deſirous of warre: What theſe men haue approued I will not altogether contradict, though I leaue it to iudgement.</p>
            <p>Now it remaines that you know out of what place, namely, whether out of the Citty, or out of the Country you may moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently chuſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vegetius</hi> would haue you to take them out of the Country, vnleſſe neceſſity doth otherwiſe conſtrayne you: and his reaſon is, that none euer douted but that theſe common rude ſort of people, were alwaies fitteſt for the warre, being brought vp abroad, vſing to take paynes, abiding Sun-burning, paſſing not for the ſhade, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer what Bathes meant,<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of dilicatnes, ſymple of mind, content with a little, hardned in euery part to abide &amp; beare labour, leaſt fearing death hauing leaſt taſted of pleaſure. This is <hi>Vegetius</hi> iudgement, which may hold in ſome, but not in all; I paſſe it ouer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:9"/>
            <p>True it is and muſt bee graunted that they of the Country who are fartheſt off from the Citty haue likely the ableſt bodies to make Souldiers, and therefore are fitteſt for the warres. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue the beſt capacities to conceiue of Souldierie, is to be doubted? ſurely they haue not, rather it is to bee expected from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Citty, or adioyning to the Citty, who haue commonly the ripeſt wittes to apprehend, and to increaſe in Souldierie: But bee it as it wil, neither of them are naturally borne Souldiers: the one may incline to warre more then the other, but the skill cometh not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out induſtery and paynes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayth, that it is neither <hi>Eurotus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopidas</note> nor the place betwixt <hi>Babix</hi> and <hi>Gnacion</hi> that bringeth forth valiant and warlike men, but they are to be found in all places where youth is brought vp in the ſhame of vice and boldneſſe to vndergoe perills for vertues ſake; <hi>Vegetius</hi> himſelfe ſayth,<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Chap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> that nature bringeth foorth few valliant men, but diligence doth make many by good inſtruction and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that in all places both cowards and hardy men are bred: And that ſome Nations yeelds better Soldiers then other.<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Hence I inferre, that Citty and Country may yeeld both good and bad Souldiers, yet the one may as farre excell the other in feats of warre, as the other excells in ſtrength of body; Chuſe then your Souldiers out of Cittie and Countrie, Often exerciſe the one, for the is dull &amp; hard to learne, make the other ſtrong, for he is actiue &amp; may get ſtrength: Let him learne to toyle and trauell,<note place="margin">☜</note> to runne too and fro, to carry burthens, to abide the Sunne and duſt:<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> let him fare hardly and homely, bee kept farre off from the allurements of the Citty: and by this meanes, both the ſtrength of his body &amp; mind ſhall be increaſed.</p>
            <p>The next chapter ſhall ſhew of what conuenient age he ſhould be, either for preſent ſeruice or Muſter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of what age Soldiers ſhould bee of for preſent ſeruice: ond a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what age young Souldiers ſhould appeare for Muſter.</head>
            <p>IF vpon a ſudden you are to raiſe an Army for expedition, my coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell is, that you will make choice of ſuch as are of mature age, about
<pb facs="tcp:9112:10"/> Eighteene, Twenty, Thirty, Forty, and more, ſtrong and luſty, able to abide heate and cold, &amp; to performe the duty of Souldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vegetius. <hi>1.</hi> Lib.</note>But if after the <hi>Romane</hi> manner you will haue young men to muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time that they muſt appeare at muſter muſt be ſo ſoone as they grow any thing to mans eſtate: this will be when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the age of 14. 15. or 16. yeares: Then not onely more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, but alſo more perfectly all thinges are learned, the ſooner the better. For <hi>Vegetius</hi> ſayth truly, that it is better that a young man exerciſed ſhould alleage that his age to fight is not yet come, then that hee ſhould truly lament that the ſame were allready paſt. Let young men then be exerciſed betimes, for it is readineſſe gotten by former practiſe that maketh a Souldier.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>Hauing in the three former Chapters diſcuſſed at large of Armes and men, and ſelected them forth to be made Soldiers: I will in the other 12. Chapters following fit them with Armes, and times of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and diſcipline, that ſo they may be deſirous of the face of the enemie and be brought forth to battell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> How Souldiers muſt bee Armed.</head>
            <p>Souldiers muſt be Armed in euery kind according as they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Dragons are light horſe men, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called Harqnebuſiers Armes of a Pikeman.</note>Souldiers are deuided into two kinds: Foot, and Horſe. The foot, againe are of two kindes; Pikemen, and Musketeirs.</p>
            <p>The Horſe men, againe into two kindes; Curaſſiers, and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gones.</p>
            <p>The Armes of Pickemen are a <hi>Gorget, Curace, Headpeece, Pike, Sword, G rdle and hangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Armes of a Muskateire.</note>The Armes of Muskateirs, are a <hi>Musket, a Reſt, Bandeleires, Headpeece, Sword, Girdle and hangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Armes of a Horſeman Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſsier.</note>The Armes of a Horſeman Curaſſier, are a <hi>Gorget, Curace, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſes, Pondrons, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ambraces, a Left-hand Gauntlet, Taces, Cuſhes, a Caske, a Sword, girdle and hangers, a caſe of Piſtolles firelockes, Saddle, Bridle, Bitt, Petrell, Crooper, with the leathers belonging to faſten his Piſtolles, and his neceſſarie ſacke of carriage, and a good Horſe to munt on.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:10"/>
            <p>The Armes of a Dragone (which hath ſucceeded in the place of alight Horſeman) are a good <hi>Harquebus</hi> or <hi>Dragone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Armes of a Dragon</note> fitted with an yron worke to be carried in a belt, a <hi>Belt with a flaske priming boxe, Key, and Bullet bagge, an open headpeece with cheekes, a Buffe coate with deepe skirts, Sword girdle and hangers, a Sadle, Bridle, Bitt, Petrell, Crooper, with ſtraps for his Sacke of neceſſaries, and a horſe of leſſe force, and leſſe price then the Curaſſiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Souldiers were diuided into two kindes, ſo are their Armes into two forts: Defenſiue, and offenſiue.</p>
            <p>Offenſiue Armes are ſuch as they indeauor to wound and kill,<note place="margin">Offenciue Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> withall as <hi>Muskets, Hargabuſes,</hi> or <hi>Dragones, Piſtolls, Pikes, Swords,</hi> and <hi>Rapiers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Defenſiue Armes,<note place="margin">Defenſiue Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> are ſuch as they weare to reſiſt the force and charge of the enemie; of this ſort are the <hi>Headpeece, Gorget, Curace, Vambraces, Gauntlet,</hi> and <hi>Taces, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Defenſiue Armes are preferred before the Offenciue,<note place="margin">Captaine Bingham in Aelian.</note> in that they bring ſafety to him that beareth them, whereas the other are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in anoying the enemie onely. Theſe Defenſiue Armes ſhould be made ſtrong, fit, and with all comely: Strong to protect or anoye, fitte, to ſit cloſe to the body, and be manageable, comelie to grace ſuch as weare them.</p>
            <p>When Souldiers are thus prouided of Armes, let them be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to weare them, for by often wearing them, their bodies will bee ſtrong, and their Armour will be no more cumberſome vnto them, then the cloathes on their backe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> did ſo inure their bodies to beare Armes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Example. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetivs.</hi> lib. 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.</note> (that as <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getius</hi> doth report of them) they would both wraſtle and run races in their Armour, and were ſo ſtrong of body by continuall vſe thereof that they made nothing of it. But when field exerciſes through negligence and ſloth was giuen ouer, Armour began to grow heauie, becauſe it was ſeldome put on.</p>
            <p>Their bodies being weakened by idleneſſe, they made ſuite to the Emperour that they might weare no more <hi>Cataphracts,</hi> nor <hi>Corſlets:</hi> Afterwards that they might lay away their <hi>Helmets,</hi> and ſo when they ſhould goe to fight againſt the <hi>Goathes,</hi> being naked on their breaſts, &amp; hauing nothing for their heads, they were often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the multitude of Archers vanquiſhed and ouercome: Therefore let Souldiers ſtill accuſtome themſelues to weare their Armour, and when want of Imployments bids them caſt them off,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:11"/> let them not forget to vſe exerciſe at home, to keepe their bodies ſtill in ſtrength: ſo when they ſhall reaſume their Armes againe, their bodies will be ſtrong and able to beare them.</p>
            <p>The next Chapter ſhewes what exerciſes they ſhould vſe; when they want imployment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> What exerciſes Souldiers ſhould vſe at idle Times, when they want imployment.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe Souldiers may want imployment, and want of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may breede idleneſſe, and idleneſſe procure a ſtiffeneſſe in the ioynts: therefore they muſt vſe at idle times ſuch exerciſes as may put life into them, which may make them ſtrong and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> for exerciſe is more auaileable then Phyſitions.</p>
            <p>The bodie by idleneſſe ingendereth many groſe and cold hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which will be very painefull to lazie Souldiers, but moderate exerciſe taken in time, will not onely preuent it, but when they are come, expelle them ſoone and giue them eaſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore let Souldiers vſe exerciſe, and ſuch exerciſes as haue in them the tokens of courage, and feates of actiuity.</p>
            <p>As Running, Leaping, Valting, and Swiming.</p>
            <p>The vſe of them followeth in the 6. 7. 8. and 9. Chapters.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Why Souldiers must vſe running</head>
            <p>THe ancient <hi>Romans</hi> did exerciſe their young Souldiers to run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that ſo with greater violence they might ſet vpon their enemies, gayne the commodious places from the enemie, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent them if they would doe the like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>For this cauſe (ſaith <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi>) they were often exerciſed to runne, that ſo being ſet out for Scouts, they might more chearefully goe forward, more readily returne, and more eaſily ouertake their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies when they fled.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:11"/>
            <p>We that doe imitate the <hi>Romans</hi> in thoſe thinges which be vſefull, doe louingly incite our Souldiers at vacant times to vſe running, that ſo they may be the better breathed, and the more able to helpe vs when we call for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The enemie being too ſtrong in ſhot for vs, we command them to runne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>that ſo we may ioyne with him ſooner; Thereby auoyding the inconuenience of playing vpon our battaile, hee hauing libertie to diſpoſe of his ſhot as he liſt himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The enemie ſeeking to gayne ſome hill, or ſtrong place by vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>we command them to runne, that ſo he may be preuented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The enemie flying, we command them to purſue him running, not in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; but in good order, for their ſafety.</hi> Thus muſt of running, now of Leaping and the vſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Why Souldiers muſt vſe Leaping.</head>
            <p>SOuldiers muſt vſe Leaping, for paſſing of deepe places, that when ſuch kind of dificulties happen, they may goe ouer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all manner of trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pompey</hi> the great excelled herein, touching whom <hi>Saluſt</hi> in this wiſe ſeemeth to make mention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the lighteſt in Leaping, with the ſwifteſt in running, with the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt he ſtroue in caſting the Barre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our gratious Soueraigne <hi>(King Charles)</hi> as a ſecond <hi>Pompey</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in this.</p>
            <p>Thus much of Running, and Leaping, now of Valting and the vſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Why Souldiers muſt vſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aulting.</head>
            <p>SOuldiers muſt vſe Vaulting to make them ready, nimble, and quicke on horſebacke.</p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Romans</hi> (ſayth <hi>Vegetius</hi>) had horſes of wood,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> which
<pb facs="tcp:9112:12"/> in winter was ſet in a houſe, in ſomer in the open field: Vpon theſe the young Souldiers were compelled to mount, at the firſt without Armour, afterwards with Armour; when being perfect, they could with ſwords and long poles in their hands get vp vpon any ſide.</p>
            <p>Let Souldiers then vſe vaulting to make them ready, nymble and quicke on horſebacke, that if it ſhould ſo chance that they were vnhorſed in battell, they might with eaſe mount themſelues vp againe and renew the fight.</p>
            <p>Thus much of Running, Leaping, and Vaulting: Now of Swym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and the vſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Why Souldiers muſt vſe Swimming.</head>
            <p>SOuldiers muſt vſe Swymming to paſſe ouer Riuers, for Bridges are not euer ready. Likewiſe in retyring, or chaſing, an Army, may be often times compelled or conſtrayned thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>Sudden ſhowers or great ſnowes (ſayth <hi>Vegetius</hi>) makes the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters breake out, and by ignorance herein Souldiers are ſubiect to danger, not onely on the behalfe of the Enemy, but alſo for drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and periſhing themſelues: for this cauſe they muſt be expert in ſwimming.</p>
            <p>The auncient <hi>Romans</hi> which by ſo many warres and contynuall perilles came to be excellent in al warre matters choſe the field <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Martius</hi> (ſayth <hi>Vegetius</hi>) hard by the Riuer <hi>Tiber,</hi> that in the ſame when they had left exerciſeing their weapons, they might waſh off all the ſweat and duſt: and when they were wearie with running, refreſh themſelues with ſwimming.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the vſe of Running, Leaping, Vaulting, Swym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; The next Chapter ſhewes vnto what, young Souldiers muſt be diſciplined, and how often trayned in a Moneth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Vnto what young Souldiers muſt bee diſciplined, and how often trayned in a Moneth.</head>
            <p>YOung Souldiers muſt be diſciplined in the right vſe of their Armes, in all the beates of the Drumme, in all militarie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;
<pb facs="tcp:9112:12"/> To march well, to Face, to Wheele, to Countermarch, to double Rankes and Files, to doe all theſe either by word of mouth, by motion of hand, or by any other mute ſigne.</p>
            <p>Therfore if you would confirme their knowledge in theſe things, it is requiſite that they ſhould be trayned either once a weeke, (or at the leaſt thrice a quarter) for continuall vſe of the thing bringeth perfectneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Latines haue giuen vs two words for an Army, <hi>Acies</hi> and <hi>Exercitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acies</hi> is latine for an Army ſet in Battell Array.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exercitus,</hi> is latine for an Army which is in exerciſe. This name denotes vnto vs, that it ſhould be euer in labour, and neuer out of practiſe.</p>
            <p>An Army therefore that is out of Exerciſe doth looſe a Name.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee muſt trayne the oftner, and in our traynings at home, practize that which may befall vs in battell abroad.</p>
            <p>This wee learne from the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The auncient <hi>Romans</hi> did vſe to trayne their yong Souldiers twice a day, their old once,<note place="margin">Vegetius. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Chap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> and this they neuer miſt what weather ſoeuer came. In faire weather they exerciſed abroad, in foule, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts erected for that purpoſe: Thrice a moneth the whole Army was brought forth to march; Their march was ten myles from the Campe: The footmen Armed &amp; furniſhed with all manner of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, the Horſemen deuided by troopes, &amp; in compleat Armes: In which march they made ſemblance of batel, the horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> began firſt.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they followed, ſometimes they gaue backe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their horſes ranne them vpon the ſpurre, not onely in plaine fields, but in ſtrange dificult places, in breaches, &amp; gapes of ditches: ſometimes the foot reſcued the horſe, ſometimes the horſe reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the foot, and both horſe and foot did aſcend and run downe high and ſteepe places.</p>
            <p>Thus were they practiſed at home, in that which might befall them abroad: ſo that happe what could happe to them in fight, theſe practized Souldiers had very well forelearned. No maruile then, though they were the conquerors of ſo many Nations. And when they neglected this, that they were ſo foyled by <hi>Haniball</hi> and his <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> foure &amp; 20. yeares they lay idle &amp; were weakened by pleaſure and difuſe of Armes: That in the ſecond warre of <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge</hi> (as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi> reporteth) they were by no meanes comparable <hi>Hanniball.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:13"/>
            <p>But after ſo many conſuls loſt, ſo many Captaines ſlaine, ſo many Armies caſt away: falling to their former exerciſe, they came at length to bee Conquerours againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh England, England remember this?</hi> By a preſumption of long ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie thou didſt bring theſe things out of vſe.</p>
            <p>But follow what thou haſt begun, and the the end will be <hi>Glory:</hi> practize <hi>Warre</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> &amp; <hi>Peace</hi> ſhall be thy reward:<note place="margin">August: de Ciuit. Dei. Lib <hi>19.</hi> Chap. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Warres</hi> end is <hi>peace.</hi> Be diligent in Trayning &amp; inſtructing thy Souldiers accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his Maieſty hath directed (euery weeke) for three monethes together, and euery holiday after in euery yeare; So thou ſhalt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the pride of thy Soueraignes Enemie, making him vnwillng to come to handy blowes, ſeeing thee ſo expert: And withall, thou ſhalt incourage the friends of thy Soueraigne, and retayne ſtill the name of a valiant victorious Nation.</p>
            <p>Therefore coueting to be victorious, ſtill practize Armes, and deſiring <hi>Peace,</hi> prepare for <hi>Warre,</hi> and ſo both will be effected.</p>
            <p>The next chapter ſhewes when young Souldiers muſt be brought forth into the field for battell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> When young Souldiers must be brought into the field for Battell.</head>
            <p>WHen they know the beates of the Drumme, the <hi>Diſtances</hi> in <hi>Rankes</hi> and <hi>Files,</hi> a <hi>Ranke</hi> from a <hi>File,</hi> and a <hi>File</hi> from a <hi>Ranke,</hi> being expert in all fights, and hauing ſuch qualities as befit Martiall Men: then let them bee brought forth into the field for Battell.</p>
            <p>For the knowledge of Warre will make them the more bold to fight: And when they are perfect in it, they will not be afraid, but take pleaſure to meet the Enemie in the field; For wee ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that no man feareth at any time to doe that which hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth himſelfe he hath throughly learned.</p>
            <p>And this may be concluded as a well grounded propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That as the well tryed and exerciſed Souldier deſires the battell, euen ſo the vnexpert and ignorant will feare the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then take with you <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi> counſell: <hi>Neuer bring your Souldiers into the field, till you haue tried and proued what they can doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Chapter ſhewes what the beates of the Drumme are, which Souldiers muſt know.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> What the beates of the Drumme are Which Souldiers muſt know.</head>
            <p>THe Drumme hath beene of long vſe, and is now for great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: The beating of which, each Souldier ought truly to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in the right name.</p>
            <p>The wiſedome of the <hi>Romans</hi> was ſuch, that when they would change their pace in March, or inflame their Souldiers in fight,<note place="margin">Reade Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rads Art of VVarre.</note> they did vſe a contrary ſound: And as the ſounds did vary, ſo likewiſe vſed they varietie of names to them: Some they called the <hi>Doricke</hi> &amp; the <hi>Phrigian</hi> ſound, the one did inflame the Souldiers hearts; The other did make meeke and appeaſe them. They had alſo the <hi>Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Iaſan,</hi> and <hi>Lidian,</hi> and diuers others which did ſerue to incite or coole the courage of Men. Which diuerſities of ſounds not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wee, but moſt Nations doe retayne vnto this day.</p>
            <p>The Drumme was firſt inuented by <hi>Bacchus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The antiquitie of the Drum.</note> from him it came into <hi>India,</hi> from <hi>India</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> from <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>Aeurope,</hi> &amp; now is vſed of all <hi>European</hi> Nations: (As the learned <hi>Captayne Bingham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) in his notes vpon <hi>Aelians Tactticks.</hi> chap. 9.</p>
            <p>The Souldier then ought to know by the Drumme,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>A Call.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>A March.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>A Troope.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>A Charge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>A Retreate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>A Battalia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>A Batterie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>A Reliefe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For when the commanders voyce cannot extend to the hearing of the company, the Drumme denounceth &amp; expreſſeth the ſame.</p>
            <p>The next Chapter ſhewes what the diſtances of Files and Rankes are, which Souldiers muſt know.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> What the diſtances in Files and Rankes are Which Souldiers muſt know.</head>
            <p>THere bee Fiue ſorts of diſtances in Files (ſay ſomme,) and they be theſe that followeth:
<list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9112:14"/>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Diſtances in Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es.</note>
                     <hi>The firſt is cloſeſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſecond is cloſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The third is order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The forth is open order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fift double diſtance.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> which is,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pouldron to pouldron</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A foote and a halfe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Three foote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sixe foote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twelue foote.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There is fiue ſorts of diſtances in Rankes ſay they:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Diſtances in Rankes.</note>
                     <hi>The firſt is cloſeſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſecond is cloſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The third is order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fourth is open order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fift double diſtance.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> which is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To the ſword poynt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Three foote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sixe foote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twelue foote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fower &amp; twenty foote.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Although they be thus ſet downe to be fiue in number, yet moſt Commanders obſerue and teach, as moſt proper, onely three. viz. <hi>Cloſe: Order:</hi> and <hi>Open order:</hi> Antiquitie had no more, yet the reſt muſt not be caſhered or ſlighted, for ſome times a commander muſt doe that in a double diſtance, which cannot be done in a ſingle.</p>
            <p>Therefore Souldiers are bound to know all diſtances in Files and Rankes, that they may the better execute what their Captayne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next Chapter ſhewes how a File and a Ranke is diſtinguiſhed for a Souldier to know.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> How a File and a Ranke is distinguiſhed for a Souldier to know.</head>
            <p>A File, is a number of men beginning at one leader and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuing in order of followers to the laſt man.<note place="margin">A diſtinction of a Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> 
               <hi>Aelian. chap.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Or thus. A File is a ſequence of men ſtanding one behind ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther backe to bellie, and conſiſteth commonly of Ten or Eight in depth.<note place="margin">Suidas.</note> The depth is no other then a File, for Rankes ſtretch forth in length, Files in depth.</p>
            <p>A Ranke is a number of men ſide to ſide, in a right line, ſtretching out in length from one end of the body vnto the other, and is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the length becauſe it runneth along the Front vnto each wing <hi>Aelian. Chap.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A diſtinction of a Ranke.</note>Or thus, A Ranke is a row of men ſtanding one by another Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron
<pb facs="tcp:9112:14"/> to pouldron, or ſhoulder to ſhoulder, their faces being directed all one way.</p>
            <p>This diſtinction of Files and Rankes a Souldier muſt know, that when he is bid to double Files, he may not Rankes, and when he is bid to double Rankes he may not Files.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next Chapter ſhewes what the fightes are which Souldiers muſt bee expertin.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> What fights they are which Souldiers muſt be expert in.</head>
            <p>THe fights neceſſary for all Souldiers to be expert in are Sixe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to fight aduancing vpon an Enemie.</p>
            <p>This is when the Enemie appeares in the vantgard,<note place="margin">To fight ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing vpon an Enemy.</note> and they by two rankes a peece march from the body ten paces, and giue fire at the place appoynted. Or when the firſt ranke giues fire (mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſtill on with the body,) and the nex ranke paſſes through by their right hand, giues fire ſtanding ſtill before them: And ſo ſtill ſucceſſiuely all the reſt in order.</p>
            <p>This is like the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Countermarch to gaine ground.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To fight retyring from an Enemie.</p>
            <p>This is when the laſt Ranke <hi>faces about</hi> to the right, giues fire,<note place="margin">To fight vpon a march, retir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vp to the Front and places themſelues before their File leaders.</p>
            <p>But if you will maintayne a ſet fight with the Enemie (to gayne a better ground) then it is requiſite you teach them the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Countermarch, making your File leaders to face about and ſtand, the reſt to paſſe through by the right hand, placing themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their leaders, and ſo meeting your Enemy in the Reare with your beſt men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To fight Front and Reare with the Enemy.</p>
            <p>This is when the middle men face about to the right,<note place="margin">To ſight Front &amp; Reare with an Enemy.</note> and all the Muskettiers fall in the diuiſion betweene both.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, To fight with both Flankes againſt an enemy ſtanding.</p>
            <p>This is when the outward File of each Flanke is commanded to face, hauing giuen fire:<note place="margin">To fight ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both Plankes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</note> each File deuideth it ſelfe into two parts, one halfe marches vp to the Front and places it ſelfe in a right line before the firſt File of Pikes. The other halfe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:9112:15"/> to the Reare, and places it ſelfe in a right line behind the bringer vp of the ſame File of Pikes: the like doth all the reſt on the contrary Flanke,<note place="margin">Captaine Bing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham, his exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</note> ſo continuing, halfe the ſhot will bee in the front, the other halfe in the Reare. Then doe but face them to the right and left by deuiſion, and each Flanke will be a battell for the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, To giue fire by Flankes vpon the Enemy marching.</p>
            <p>This is when both their outward Files next to the Enemie makes readie,<note place="margin">To fight mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching both flankes againſt an en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mie.</note> faces to either hand, giues fire at command, ſtayes till the reſt of all the Files bee cleare of them; Then marches vp by the Pikes, till all the reſt doing the like, bringes them againe to their firſt place.</p>
            <p>Or when they giue fire and ſtand, and being (as it were in two Files) the body of Pickes marching, an officer comes, and gathers vp the winges &amp; ioynes them againe in equall front with the Pikes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt horſe in a ſet battell for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt an enemy.</note>Sixtly, To fight againſt horſe in a ſet battell for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This is when they countermarch their winges into the midſt of the battell, and are impaled round with Pikes, and ſo drawne forth on either ſide vnder the ſhelter of them.</p>
            <p>In theſe ſixe fights your Souldiers muſt bee very expert, that they may auoyd all confuſion. And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the Twelue Chapters before mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>The next two Chapters declare what qualities they are which befit Martiall men, and how requiſite it is for them to bee wiſe and politicke to preſerue the liues of their men, and how politicke wiſedome may be attayned, with a briefe Summarie thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> What qualities they are which befitt Martiall Men.</head>
            <p>THe qualities which befit Martiall men are many, but I will at this time treate but of Eight, and they be theſe, <hi>viz. Silence. Obedience. Secrecie. Sobriety. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alour. Loyalty. Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from Bribes. Moderation in expence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt: <hi>Silence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIlence</hi>
               <note place="margin">Silence.</note> was of ſuch veneration amongſt the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> that they made thereof a God, which with them was called <hi>Harpocrates:</hi> and according to the Greekes <hi>Sigaleon:</hi> him they portratured in the
<pb facs="tcp:9112:15"/> likeneſſe of a young childe,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de ciuit. Dei, li. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> who cloſe to his lips held one of his fingers: ſometimes they pictured him without any face at all, all couered ouer with the skin of a Wolfe, on which were depainted as many eyes and eares as could be inſerted thereon, ſignifying thereby that it was needfull to ſee and heare much, and to ſpeake little, in that he that ſpeaketh not, offendeth not. All this is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note vnto vs the excellencie of Silence, which is commendable in all men, but eſpecially in Souldiers, who muſt rule their tongues and be ſilent, or elſe they will ſoone periſh and come to nought. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith that there is no danger in ſilence.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Homer</hi> highly commendeth it in the <hi>Grecians,</hi> in his deſcriptions of their fights with the <hi>Troians.</hi> His words be theſe:
<q>
                  <l>The Captaines marſhall out their troopes, ranged in goodly guiſe,</l>
                  <l>And forth the Troians pace like birds, which lade the aire with cries.</l>
                  <l>Not ſo the Greekes, whoſe ſilence breathed flames of high deſire,</l>
                  <l>Feruent in zeale to backe their friends, on foes to wreake their ire.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And in another place ſpeaking of the <hi>Grecians;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>You ſurely would haue deem'd each one, of all that mighty throng</l>
                  <l>Had beene bereft of ſpeech, ſo bridled he his tongue.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of Silence. The next qualitie for a Souldier is Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obedience</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obedience.</note> is the Queene of vertues, and crownes her followers with the wreathes of honour. It effecteth much with few, and gaines the victory ouer multitudes. Therefore let Souldiers obey their Commanders, for without Obedience nothing can be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulus Aemylius</hi> being to obſerue the cuſtome of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> and to make an Oration of thanks vnto the people for chuſing him Conſull, in his Oration told them, That if they had any truſt or confidence in him, or thought him a man ſufficient to diſcharge his place, that then they ſhould not ſpeake nor meddle in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concerned his dutie and the office of a Generall, ſauing only that they would be diligent without any words to doe whatſoeuer he commanded, that ſhould be neceſſary for the warres and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice they tooke in hand.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Aemylius</hi> 250.</note> All which (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) the <hi>Romans</hi> obeyed, and by yeelding vnto reaſon and vertue, came to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb facs="tcp:9112:16"/> all other, and to make themſelues the mightieſt people of the world. And indeed they were the moſt obedient to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of any; inſomuch as a certaine <hi>Numidian</hi> asking young <hi>Scipio</hi> how he would conquer <hi>Carthage, Scipio</hi> vpon a hill poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with his finger to his Souldiers below, anſwered him thus: <hi>With theſe I will conquer Carthage; for if I ſhould bid them from hence caſt themſelues downe headlong, know they will doe it.</hi> How ſeuerely the Conſuls did puniſh diſobedience in the campe,<note place="margin">Examples of rigorous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for diſobedience.</note> may appeare by the rigorous puniſhment which <hi>Manlius Torquatus</hi> did execute vpon his ſonne <hi>Titus Manlius,</hi> commanding his head to be ſtricken off in his owne preſence, for hauing paſſed his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in ſallying forth to fight with <hi>Genutius M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius</hi> Captaine of the <hi>Tuſeulans,</hi> who gaue him the defie and challenge. Nothing auailing the poore Gentleman in hauing ouercome and ſlaine his enemie, nor the whole Armies ſupplications and intreaties. The like rigour vſed <hi>Poſthumus Tiburtus</hi> againſt his ſonne <hi>Aulus Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humus,</hi> at his returne from his conquered enemie. All this to ſhew the excellencie of obedience,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> which the Prophet prefers above ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifice. Thus much of Obedience. The next qualitie for a Souldier is Secrecie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secrecie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secrecie.</note> is a quali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie appropriated to none but wiſe men; for a foole hauing heard a ſecret, trauelleth as a woman with childe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcloſed i; but a wiſe man keepeth it cloſe in his breaſt, and when any goes about to commit a ſecret vnto him, he will ſeeke all meanes to auoid it. King <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> as he aduiſed and talked vpon a time with <hi>Philippedes</hi> (the Comicall Poet) a friend and familiar of his, he ſaid vnto him, <hi>What wouldeſt thou haue me to impart vnto thee of all that mine is? Euen what it ſhall pleaſe you Sir</hi> (anſwered the Poet) <hi>ſo it be none of your ſecrets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anacharſis,</hi> being inuited one day and feaſted by <hi>Solon,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted wiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Morals.</note> for that being aſleepe, he was found and ſeene holding his right hand to his mouth, and his left vpon his priuities and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parts. Hence <hi>Plutarch</hi> inferres this, That he had good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo to think, becauſe the Tongue required and needed the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bridle to reſtraine it, being a hard matter to reckon ſo many perſons vndone and ouerthrowne by their vntemperate and loofe life, as there haue beene Cities and mightie States ruinated and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vtterly, by the reuealing and opening of ſome ſecrets. Therefore let all men ſtriue to attaine this vertue of ſecrecie;<note place="margin">☞</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:9112:16"/> Souldiers, for by their ouer-much babling, they may be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the ouerthrow of themſelues and others.</p>
            <p>A ſtrange accident did happen to the City of <hi>Athens,</hi> (which <hi>Sylla</hi> did beleager) through the lauiſhneſſe of certaine vnbrideled tongues.<note place="margin">☜ Plutarch.</note> Certaine old fellowes being met in a Barbers ſhop with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City of <hi>Athens</hi> (being blabs of their tongues) chatted it out in their talke together, that a certaine quarter of the Citie, named <hi>Heptacaleon,</hi> was not ſufficiently guarded, &amp; therefore the Towne in danger to be ſurpriſed, by that part; which talke of theirs was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-heard by certaine Eſpies, who aduertiſed <hi>Sylla</hi> ſo much, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon immediately he brought all his Forces to that ſide, and about midnight gaue an aſſault, made entrie, and went within a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of forcing the City, and being Maſter of it all; for he filled the whole ſtreet, called <hi>Ceranicum,</hi> with ſlaughter and dead carkaſſes, in ſo much that the channels ran downe with bloud. A fearefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, That <hi>words haue wings, and when they flie out they cannot be recalled backe againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Symonides</hi> ſaith, <hi>A man may repent many times for words ſpoken, but neuer for a word kept in.</hi> The Kings of <hi>Perſia</hi> did puniſh with death the lauiſhneſſe of the tongue. This made the <hi>Perſians</hi> famous for ſecrecie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> reports thus of them, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, ſaith he, wrought all the wayes he could, to obtaine knowledge where <hi>Darius</hi> was become, and into what Countrey he was gone, and yet could not get the intelligence; by reaſon of a cuſtome among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which were wont with a maruellous fidelity to keepe cloſe their <hi>Princes</hi> ſecrets, in the vttering whereof, neither death nor hope of reward could cauſe them to bring forth a word, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in thoſe parts) not any goodneſſe looked for at any mans hands, that hath not the gift of ſecretneſſe, whereof Nature hath giuen a facillity in man. Thus much of Secrecie. The next vertue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a Souldier, is Sobriety or Temperance.</p>
            <p>Sobriety is a great vertue, and greatly to be accounted of all men,<note place="margin">Sobrietie.</note> for it extinguiſheth Vice in the cradle, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h it in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed. It is the mother of health, &amp; an aſſured medicine againſt all maladies, and that which lengtheneth a mans life. <hi>Socrates</hi> by Sobrietie had alwaies a ſtrong body, and liued euer in health; whereas <hi>Alexander,</hi> by his drunkenneſſe, dyed in the flower of his age, though he were
<pb facs="tcp:9112:17"/> better borne, and of a ſounder conſtitution than <hi>Socrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the greateſt Perſonages of the world haue beene Sober.</p>
            <p>So was <hi>Cyrus</hi> the elder, ſo was <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo was <hi>Iulian</hi> the Emperor.</p>
            <p>Therefore let all Souldiers be ſober, and embrace Sobriety, for it will make them as Kings and Princes to gouerne their paſſions, and to bridle their inſatiate appetite. To Sobrietie let them adde Temperance.</p>
            <p>Temperance<note place="margin">Temperance.</note> is a rule that ſweetly accommodateth al things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Nature, Neceſſity, Simplicity, Facility, Health, Conſtancie. Temperance will weane their ſoules from the ſweet milke of the pleaſures of this world, and make them capable of a more ſolide and ſoueraigne nouriſhment. Theſe two will highly aduance them in the fauour of their Generall, and raiſe them in time to great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, whereas drunkards and vntemperate perſons are contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of all men, and no matter of importancie to be committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.<note place="margin">Reade <hi>Garrards</hi> Art of War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> The <hi>Turkes</hi> are famous for their Sobriety. A certaine Gentleman, at his returne from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> did declare vnto the Earle of <hi>Salma,</hi> that he had ſeene foure miracles in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; which was, firſt an infinite Armie almoſt without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, conſiſting of more than foure hundred thouſand men: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that amongſt ſo many men bee ſaw not one woman: Thirdly, that there was no mention made of wine: Laſtly, at night when they had cried with a high voice, <hi>Alla,</hi> which is <hi>God,</hi> there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſo great a ſilence thorow the whole Campe, that euen in the Pauilions they did not ſpeake but in a low voice. A thing worthy to be admired and imitated, though from <hi>Turkes.</hi> The next Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie required in a Souldier is Valour.</p>
            <p>Valour<note place="margin">Valour.</note> is the greateſt, the moſt generous and heroycalleſt vertue for a Souldier of all other, it conſiſteth in the ſtoutneſſe of his heart, in the reſolution and ſtayedneſſe of his minde, grounded vpon the dutie, the honeſty, and iuſtice of the enterpriſe, which reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neuer ſlacketh whatſoeuer hapneth, vntill he haue valiantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the enterpriſe, or his life. Here is Valour, let Souldiers ſtriue to be thus valiant: ſome doe ſeeke this vertue in the body, and in the power and ſtrength of the limmes. But they are miſtaken, for it is not a qualitie of the body, but of the minde, a ſetled ſtrength, not of the armes and legs,<note place="margin">They terme it.</note> but of the courage. This Valour is <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall,</hi> not altogether humane, being an impregnable bulwarke, a compleat armour to incounter all accidents, arming a man againſt
<pb facs="tcp:9112:17"/> his owne aduerſe fortune,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter Charron</hi> of Wiſdome, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 499.</note> and making him to brooke the conſtancy and vertue of his enemy, containing Magnanimity, Patience, and other chiefe heroicall vertues: All other helps are ſtrange and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed: ſtrength of armes &amp; legs is the quality of a Porter; to make an enemy to ſtoope, to daſle his eyes at the light of the Sunne, is an accident of Fortune.</p>
            <p>He whoſe courage faileth not for feare of death, quelleth not in his conſtancy and reſolution, and though he fall is not vanquiſhed of his Aduerſary (who perhaps may in effect, be but a baſe fellow,) but of Fortune: and therefore he is to accuſe his owne vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not his negligence;<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>The moſt valiant are oftentimes the moſt vnfortunate.</hi> Seeing it is ſo; Let no man be diſheartned, eſpecially a <hi>Souldier,</hi> ſeeing he muſt be brought vnto ſome honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable enterpriſe, and therefore not to aduenture, is cowardneſſe, to aduenture on, valour, be the euent what it will. Many are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted valiant, who haue no ſparke of true Valour in them; ſuch are all our <hi>Thraſonicall Braggadoſhes, Ragamuffin Rorers,</hi> who will quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with any man they meet with for the Wall, and ſend their challenges abroad as oftentations of their Valour. But ſuch are not to be dealt withall, being but raſh men, baſtardly Valorous,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter Charron</hi> of Wiſdome, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 500.</note> as they call it. True Valour, though it be Humane, is a wiſe Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; a Feare accompanied with foreſight to auoid one euill by another: and ſuch men as are thus valorous, will not venture their life vpon any ſleight occaſion. Theſe are wiſe and are to be commended; the other vnwiſe, and are to bee diſcommended. <hi>Cato</hi> the elder, hearing many to commend a hare-braind fellow for his Valour, wittily taunted the applauſers thus: <hi>My friends</hi> (quoth he) <hi>I wonder why you ſhould eſteeme Valour ſo much, and Life ſo little. Plutarch</hi> againſt heady Raſhneſſe ſpeaketh to this effect, and ſaith; That when King <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſent his Herald vnto King <hi>Antigonus;</hi> to challenge him to fight, <hi>Antigonus</hi> made him this anſwer, That he made Warres as much with <hi>Time</hi> as with <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons;</hi> and if <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> were weary of his Life, there was enough open to put himſelfe to death. Thus you ſee how heady Raſhneſſe is to be contemned and auoided. But this doth no whit impeach Valour, for Valour executed in fit time and place, hath produced wonderfull effects. <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that hee got the Victory at <hi>Arbella,</hi> more by his owne Vertue than by any Fortune; and that with Valour and hardneſſe more then through
<pb facs="tcp:9112:18"/> any aduantage of ground.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith of <hi>Cains Martius;</hi> That by his meere Valour and manhood, he tooke the City of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioles;</hi> and after was the cauſe of the Conſul <hi>Cominius</hi> victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, which came to the reſcue of it. For the <hi>Volfes</hi> (fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the taking of the City) came from all parts of the Countrey to ſaue it, and had diuided themſelues into two parts, to hold the <hi>Romanes</hi> play in two ſeuerall places.) Therefore <hi>Martius</hi> hauing taken their City, left the ſpoile thereof to his obſtinate Souldiers which ſtayed behind, and with a few that willingly offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to goe, he went to aide the Conſul <hi>Cominius</hi> againſt the reſt. When he came he asked him how the Order of the Enemies Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell was, and on which ſide they had placed the beſt fighting men. The Conſul made him anſwer, that he thought the Bands which were in the Vaward of their Battell, were thoſe of the <hi>Antiates,</hi> whom they eſteemed the warlikeſt men, and which for courage would giue no place to any of the Hoaſt of their Enemies. Then prayed <hi>Martius</hi> to bee ſet directly againſt them; the Conſul granted him, greatly praiſing his courage. Then <hi>Martius,</hi> when both the Armies came almoſt to ioyne, aduanced himſelfe a good ſpace before his Company, and went ſo fiercely to giue charge on the Vaward that came right againſt him, that they could ſtand no longer in his hands, he made ſuch a lane through them, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a paſſage into the Battell of the Enemies. The <hi>Romanes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing againſt their foes, beſought <hi>Martius</hi> that he would returne to the Campe, becauſe they ſaw he was able to doe no more, hee was already ſo wearied with the great paine he had taken, and ſo faint with the great wounds he had vpon him. But <hi>Martius</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them, that it was not for Conquerors to yeeld, nor to bee faint-hearted; and thereupon began afreſh to chaſe them that fled, vntill ſuch time as the Army of the Enemies was vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and numbers of them ſlaine and taken priſoners. The next morning betimes, <hi>Martius</hi> went to the Conſul <hi>Cominius,</hi> who highly commended him for his Valour, and proffered him many gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, but <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtius</hi> refuſed all. Therefore the Conſul did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and decree, that he ſhould henceforth be called <hi>Coriolanus,</hi> in lieu of the noble ſeruice he had done, &amp; for his Lion-like courage.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much of Valour.</p>
            <p>The next Vertue required in a Souldier is Loyalty.<note place="margin">Loyalty.</note> Loyalty is a tranſcendent Vertue, and paſſeth my power to expreſſe. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb facs="tcp:9112:18"/> in the faithfulnes of Subiects to their Prince, of Souldiers to their General, of one friend to another. For without faith no friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Faith is the band of all humane ſociety, the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, &amp; aboue all things ought to be religiouſly obſerued. The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> were wont to exact it from their Souldiers by an oath, the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me whereof (in <hi>Vegetius</hi> time) did run thus:<note place="margin">Vegeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We ſweare by God the Father, by Chriſt his Sonne, and by the Holy Ghoſt, to do all thing: valiantly which the Emperour or Prince doth command vs; we will neuer forſake the warre, neither refuſe death for the Romane Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> This ſhewes what manner of man a Souldier ſhould be, loyall and faithfull, ſuch a one by nature, not by Arte or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; therefore let all Souldiers ſtriue to attaine this excellent vertue of Loyalty, which will ſo arme them againſt all the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Enemy, as he ſhall neuer be able to make them Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.<note place="margin">☜</note> What Souldier would become a Traitor to betray his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or Captaine into the hands of his Enemy, if he did conſider the penalty of the ſame; it may bee from him that ſets him on worke? I will inſtance it in the <hi>Argyraſpides.</hi>
               <note place="margin">They loue the Treaſon but they hate the Traitor. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Eume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Pauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Argyraſpides</hi> were old Souldiers of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who did deliuer their good Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Eumones</hi> aliue into the hands of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> his deadly enemy. But <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who ſet them a worke, commanded euery mothers ſonne of them to be ſlaine in recompence of their Treaſon, (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Eumenes.</hi>) Treaſon is a horrid fact, and the iuſtice of God will not let it paſſe vnpuniſhed, be the committer neuer ſo great: I will inſtance it in <hi>Pauſanias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Pauſanias</hi> was Generall of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> when the <hi>Perſians</hi> ouer-ran <hi>Greece,</hi> and waſted all the Country before them, he receiued of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> fiue hundred Talents of gold, promiſing him to betray <hi>Sparta:</hi> but his Treaſon being diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> his father purſued him into the Temple of <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> called <hi>Chalciaecos,</hi> where he fled for Sanctuary, where he cauſed the doores of the Temple to be mured vp with bricke, and famiſhed him to death: his mother tooke his corps, and caſt it forth to the dogs, not ſuffering it to bee buried, ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Pauſanias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe examples being ſet before their eyes, will not only make them to deteſt Treaſon, but to become more faithfull vnto their Commanders.</p>
            <p>Of all Souldiers none euer were more faithfull to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders
<pb facs="tcp:9112:19"/> than the Romans, ye ſhall not read in any Hiſtory of any faithfuller Souldiers than they haue beene.</p>
            <p>When their Conſull <hi>Craſſus</hi> was endangered by the Parthian Arrowes, which flew thicke about his eares, they did compaſſe him about, and brought him into the middeſt of them, then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering him round with their Targets, they told him, That neuer Arrow of the Parthians ſhould touch his body, before they were all ſlaine, one after another, fighting it out to the laſt man in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Otho</hi> the Emperour.</note>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports a more admirable act of theirs than this. The Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> (ſaith he) was forſaken of all his Captaines, who had yeelded themſelues to <hi>Vitellus,</hi> the new Emperour, his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers notwithſtanding forſooke him nor, neither went they to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues to their enemies the Conquerours, neither tooke they any regard of themſelues to ſee their Emperor in that deſpaire, but all ioyntly together went vnto his lodging and called for their Emperour; when hee came out, they fell downe at his feet; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated thus on the ground, they did kiſſe his hands, with the teares running downe their cheekes, and beſought him, not to forſake and leaue them to their enemies, but to command their perſons, whileſt they had one drop of blood left in their bodies to doe him ſeruice:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>Then one of the poore Souldiers, drawing out his ſword, ſaid vnto him, Know, O <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that all my Companions are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to dye in this ſort for thee; and ſo ſlew himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe were faithfull and loyall Souldiers, worthy to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred to all poſterities: They were conſtant to their friends, faithfull to one another; not refuſing death for the Romane Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>Let all Souldiers imitate them in faithfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Faithfull Souldiers are a Captaines bulwarke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſafer in the Campe then in the Senate.</p>
            <p>Thus much of loyalty.</p>
            <p>The next quality required from a Souldier, is freedome from bribes.</p>
            <p>It is a diſhonourable thing for a Souldier to receiue a Bribe; and it is the more diſhonourable, becauſe the law of Armes doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it: wherefore doth the law of Armes ſtrictly forbid it with a penalty to the ſame, but becauſe thoſe men, whoſe nature is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:9112:19"/> prone to take bribes, are the moſt fitteſt to be made Traytors? On them the enemy will lay golden bookes, to draw them to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, vpon any occaſion. Thus <hi>Xerxes</hi> dealt with <hi>Arthmius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticles.</hi>
               </note> borne at Zelb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a, who by gold was to corrupt the Graecians, to make him way into Greece. But <hi>Arthmius</hi> was thereupon noted of infamy, not alone, but his children, with their poſterity after.</p>
            <p>Thus he dealt with <hi>Pauſanius,</hi> Generall of the Lacedemonians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xerxes</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Pauſanius</hi> with 500 ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of gold to betray Sparta. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Morals, and in the life of <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanius.</hi>
               </note> to whom he gaue fiue hundred Talents of gold, to betray <hi>Sparta</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands: but <hi>Pauſanius,</hi> being too much gorged with gold, was mured vp in a Temple, and famiſhed to death, as I haue already declared.</p>
            <p>Good reaſon therefore it is, that the law of Armes ſhould ſo ſtrictly forbid the taking of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ibes, ſeeing the whole Army may be endangered thereby. And the law of Armes doth likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all acceptance of gifts, as vnlawfull for any to receiue of a profeſſed enemy, that is, or hath beene, or may be gueſſed at to bee hereafter, whether they be giuen him in lieu of his deſert, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence him for his Ambaſſage; he muſt not, I ſay, accept them of him, forfeare of bringing himſelfe into danger. Haue not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bin brought into ſuſpition by it? Haue not ſome loſt their liues for it? Read Hiſtories, peruſe this example.</p>
            <p>The Athenians ſent their Ambaſſadors (who were Souldiers) to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> King of Perſia, to fulfill the deſire of the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Pelopidas</hi> pag. 302.</note> and to grant him peace: The King was ſo pleaſed therewith, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained them royally, and ſent them backe againe with many gifts; but when they were returned home, they were deſeruedly checked by their State and Communalty, who had them all in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition; and ſome had much adoe to cleare themſelues. Among them was one <hi>Timagoras,</hi> who had receiued of the King of Perſia, foureſcore milch Kine, for the peale, and other preſents, with a great deale of gold and ſiluer, him the Athenians condemned to dye, and neither wealth nor friends could ſaue his life. This ſhould make a Souldier to beware how he takes gifts or preſents from an enemy, leſt he loſe his life, or incurre the ill will of his Prince, or be of no repute among men.</p>
            <p>What made <hi>Pelopidas</hi> to be ſo well reputed of among the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Pelopidas</hi> pag. 303.</note> but becauſe he refuſed the gifts and preſents which the King of Perſia offered him? What made <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſo highly to commend <hi>Manius Curius?</hi> but becauſe he refuſed the gifts which the Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites
<pb facs="tcp:9112:20"/> ſent vnto him by their Ambaſſadors? This <hi>Manius Curius</hi> was a Romane and had triumphed thrice, being the greateſt man of Rome in his time, hauing ſubdued the mightieſt nations and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Italy; and driuen King <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> alſo out of the ſame; yet himſelfe dwelt in a little farme, hauing a ſmall patch of ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto, being therewith contented, and manuring the ſame with his owne hands: thither notwithſtanding, after his three triumphs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Marcus Cato.</hi>
               </note> the Samnits ſent their Ambaſſadors to viſit him, who found him by the fire ſide, ſeething of Parſnips, and preſented him a maruellous deale of gold from their State and Communalty; but <hi>Curius</hi> returned them againe with their gold, and told them, That ſuch as were contented with that Supper, had no need of gold or ſiluer; and that for his part, he thought it greater honour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them that had gold, then to haue it himſelfe.</p>
            <p>They who will immitate this man, ſhall inherite his commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: I conclude with this admonition to all Souldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Truſſell,</hi> in his Souldiers plea.</note>Let them not receiue any thing from the enemy, either gift or letter, or any ſuch thing; no, though it be from their owne fathers, without the licenſe of their Generall or Captaines; if they doe, they will bee wonderfully ſuſpected, and in danger, not onely of their credits, but alſo of their liues.</p>
            <p>The next quality required in a Souldier, is <hi>Moderation</hi> in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
            <p>Moderation in expence<note place="margin">Moderate in expence.</note> is not onely profitable, but commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. Therefore let Souldiers be moderate in expence, rather ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring than waſting.</p>
            <p>The ancient Romans were commendable for this, the halfe of that which was giuen them in the warres, they ſet apart by their Standards, there to be kept, leſt through exceſſe and ryot, or the getting of vaine things, it might bee waſted by themſelues or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but being by their Standards they knew it ſafe. This made them neuer to forſake their Standards, but rather ſticke to them: ſo when they came home from the warres, they brought that with them that was able to maintaine them. The next Chapter ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what the wiſdome and policy is which ought to bee in euery Commander.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of Wiſdome and Policy; the vſe of it; how it may be attained: with a briefe Summary of ſtratagems and policies, pertinent for theſe times, divulged for ſuch as haue the command ouer thouſands: I meane, for young Commanders, not old Soldiers.</head>
            <p>WIſdome and Policie is fit for euery Souldier,<note place="margin">Of wiſdome &amp; policy, the vſe of it, and how it may be attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. &amp;c.</note> but more proper for thoſe Commanders before mentioned; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt ſtudie to get wiſdome and policy, for it is the onely meanes, next vnder God, whereby they may preſerue their owne liues, and the liues of their Souldiers. If a Captaine bee void of wiſdome and learning, Martial diſcipline wanteth her greateſt ſtay; courage proueth raſhneſſe, and policy will be but weakely ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Learning in a Souldier (ſaith <hi>Vegetius</hi>) is an Armour of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tainted proofe, and a wounding Dart vnreſiſtable: Therefore let Soldiers, if it be poſſible, ſtudy to attaine to learning: learning is obtained by induſtry and inſtruction, as policy and wiſdome by experience.</p>
            <p>The way to attaine wiſdome and Policy,<note place="margin">Read <hi>Xenophons</hi> Hiſtorie of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> Warres. Read <hi>Frontines</hi> booke of Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, now extant, and commonly ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getius.</hi> Read <hi>Plutarchs</hi> liues, the Turkiſh Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and many others; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of euery Nation now extant in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh.</note> is to be frequent in the reading of Hiſtories; eſpecially of ſuch Hiſtories as are ſtored with worthy ſtratagems, and the braue exploits of worthy Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals: There young Commanders ſhall finde ſtore of examples, and be taught to obſerue euery one of theſe particulars;</p>
            <p n="1">1 When they are to take a iourney, and to make warre with an enemie in his owne Countrey, they muſt by all meanes get aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, by intelligencers, of all the difficult paſſages of the ſame, the ſhortneſſe of the waies, the turnings, the mountaines, and all the riuers that are therein, leſt in going they ſuffer inuaſion of the enemie, to their detriment, or finall deſtruction: but being pread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, they are halfe armed, and preuent the danger with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle loſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When they are prepared, and ſetting forth to march, there muſt be this warineſſe and heed taken that it be not knowne or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged abroad vnto what places they goe, nor by what waies they meane to paſſe, for that iourney is taken in hand without feare,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:21"/> which the enemy doth not ſo much as once ſuſpect.</p>
            <p>The two famous Souldiers of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Greece,</hi> which ſhot like two thunder bolts into the Weſt and Eaſt, and filled the whole world with the fame of their Victories, are renowned for nothing more then their celerity in doing and preuenting the very report of their comming.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>They who would arriue at the Port of Victory, and by her gates enter the Tower of Fame, muſt keepe their intentions ſecret.</p>
            <p>Old <hi>Metellus</hi> being importunated by an inſinuating friend of his touching the army, and ſetting forward of ſome expedition, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him thus: If I will (quoth hee) that my ſhirt which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my skin knew this my inward intent and ſecret purpoſe, I would put it off and fling it into the fire</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vegetius lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>The old men of warre (ſaith <hi>Vegetius</hi>) had in then Legions the badge and ſigne of the <hi>Minotaure,</hi> that as he was ſaid to be hid in the innermoſt and moſt ſecret place of the Labyrinth, euen ſo the intent of the Captaine ſhould be kept ſecret and hid, therefore it muſt be kept cloſe, vnto what places and by what wayes they meane to paſſe forth. But becauſe Spies ſent out on the other party doe either ſee or ſuſpect which way they are intended to goe, and many times there wanteth not Runnagates or Traitors. In the next place it ſhall be declared how theſe things at hand may be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and reſiſted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When they are vpon their march, they muſt ſend moſt truſtie and fine witted men, with the beſt tried horſe, which muſt ſearch the places thorow which they muſt take their iourney, before and behinde, on the right hand and on the left hand, leſt the enemie goe about to ſet an ambuſhment, and lie in wait to deceiue them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When they haue diſcried an Ambuſh, they muſt compaſſe the ſame about politikely; ſo it ſhall ſuffer more perill and danger than it went about to doe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When they approach nigh vnto the enemie, they muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue to know what manner of man their aduerſarie is, what his Companions are and Leaders, whether they be raſh and haſtie, or warie and circumſpect, whether they be hardy, or fearefull, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the feats of warre, or ſuch as are wont to fight at all aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; whether they excell or exceed them in number of men, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and fence of armour; whether they can doe more with foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or horſemen; with Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emen, or Muſquetiers; whether by
<pb facs="tcp:9112:21"/> night, or in the dawning of the day, or in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of repaſt, their cuſtome be to aſſaile their wearied enemies. Then to debate and treat of their owne power, what may be done in this caſe; whether it be more profitable to prolong the vrgent neceſſitie of battell, or to fight it out of hand. If they know themſelues to haue the better Horſemen, the better Footmen, the better Souldiers, the better furniſhed in many things, let them not deferre the conuenient and fit occaſion of figh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing. But if they perceiue their enemies to be the better, let them auoid the open and ſet battell, for a few in number and weake in ſtrength, oftentimes vnder good Captaines haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the victory, by ſudden inuaſions and lying priuily in wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which they may doe, taking time.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When they are reſolued to aduenture a ſet battell with the enemie, they are firſt to ſound the mindes and diſpoſitions of their Souldiers, whether they ſtand affected to fight or no, (it being as they would haue it) they muſt begin to forecaſt how to get the Sunne, the Wind and Duſt, in the face of the enemie. The higher ground likewiſe, to the intent the enemie may fight both againſt them and the place; for theſe are not the leaſt meanes of obtaining the victorie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When they hope for victory through Footmen, againſt the Horſemen of their enemies, they muſt chuſe ruffe places, vneuen, and full of hils. But if they looke to gaine the victory through Horſemen, againſt the Footmen of their enemies, they muſt chuſe ſuch places as be indeed ſomewhat higher, but plaine and open, encumbred neither with woods nor ſennes.</p>
            <p n="8">8 When they haue cunningly incompaſt the battels of their enemies, they muſt leaue them ſome way whereby they may flie, for if a paſſage to depart away be once opened, as ſoon as the minds of all doe agree to runne away; they are ſlaine and murdered like beaſts. Neither is there any danger to purſue them, when they haue flung downe their weapons and will fight no longer but being ſo incloſed, that they haue no way to flie, they fight ſtoutly, and become deſperately deſperate, becauſe they looke for no ſafetie or life; ſo you haue no oddes at all, but are both indifferent alike. For they are as couragious and as deſperate to fight as you, rather more, by the occaſion. Therefore young <hi>Scipio's</hi> counſell is to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed:<note place="margin">☜</note> The way whereby the enemie may flie muſt not bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:22"/>9 When they are not reſolued to fight, but to depart away from the enemie, the Souldiers muſt not know that they doe it to ſhunne battell, but they muſt bee brought in beliefe that they are called back for this policie: That the enemie may be allured vnto a more conuenient place, that he may be the more eaſily vanquiſhed and intrapped by them.<note place="margin">Vegetius lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> This they muſt not faile to doe, (for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetius</hi> ſaith) they will be readie to flie, if they perceiue their owne Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aines to deſpaire.</p>
            <p n="10">10 When their enemies doth perceiue their flight, then their care muſt be to ſend ſome before to poſſeſſe the places of greateſt aduantage which the enemie doth couet, that the reſt may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſe in ſafety, and the enemy be fruſtrated of his purpoſe. Others behind muſt lie in ambuſh to intrap the enemy who comes on with boldneſſe, no whit ſuſpecting this policy. The reſt muſt be pread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to be euer in readineſſe, leſt the ſudden co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of their enemies make them fearefull:</p>
            <p n="11">11 When they are in feare to bee incloſed by the number of their enemies, they muſt either ſeeke ſome place of naturall defence, or make the place ſo by art. I will explaine both by examples.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to chooſe a ground to fight with an enemie, when you feare to come into the champion to be incloſed by his number. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſlaus.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ageſilau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and hauing to do with a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> of whom he ſtood in feare of, to abide them battell in the champion, by reaſon of their multitude, did thus: He brought his men into the field. One while hee made as though hee fled, and inticed them to follow him; ſuddenly againe he would turne this way, and that way, in fine he brought all this multitude into a ſtrait ſluce walled about on either ſide, with great broad dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches full of running water, ſo that euen when they were in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of it, he ſuddenly ſtopped their paſſage with the front of his battaile, which he caſt to the breadth of the ſluce, and thus made the number of his fighting men equal with the number of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who could neuer compaſſe him in behinde, nor flanke him on the ſides.<note place="margin">☞</note> This he did by chooſing a place fit for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to fortifie a pl ce by art.</note>The place may be helped by art, in caſe it be otherwiſe too open, and fit for the enemy, that abounds in number, to incompaſſe them on euery ſide.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Caeſar</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Caeſar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bello Gall. lib. <hi>2. 36.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>3. 323.</hi>
               </note> being to fight againſt multitudes of <hi>Gaules,</hi> drew a deepe Trench on both the Flankes of his army, to ſecure it from the charge of the enemie. The like did <hi>Sylla</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Plutarch. in Syla, &amp; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. in bello Mitbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates.</note> againſt <hi>Archelaus,</hi> the Generall of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> in the battell of <hi>Orchomene,</hi> and both of
<pb facs="tcp:9112:22"/> them ſo ſecuring their armies from circumuention, became Maſters of the Field, and Conquerours of their enemies. Of latter times <hi>Iohn Huniades</hi> the <hi>Hungarian</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Turkiſh. Hiſt.</hi> 297. §. 2.</note> King, being to fight againſt the huge armie of the <hi>Turke,</hi> gained a noble battell againſt them, by placing his armie on the one ſide againſt a Fenne, and incloſing it on the other ſide with his Waggons.</p>
            <p n="12">12. When they cannot preuaile againſt the Enemy by ſtrength, then let them miniſter and breed cauſes of diſcord amongſt their Souldiers; for no Army, though it be very little, can quickly be deſtroyed of the Enemies, except it be conſumed with priuate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions and hatred within it ſelfe. This is practiſed to this day, and is tollerated by our chiefes of Warre, who prefer policy before ſtrength, therefore let it be followed. The old <hi>Spartan</hi> that had conquered by policie, offered an Oxe; but he that preuailed by force, offered only a Cocke; becauſe the greater ſacrifice of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, was due to the gods from him, for the one; and the greater praiſe and reward was due vnto him, from the State for the other. But this is the greateſt glory of all to driue out the naile of their Enemies practiſe, with a ſtronger of their owne, and to blow him vp in his owne Mine. Policie againſt force deſerueth much, and preuaileth often; but by Stratagem to preuaile againſt Policy is euer excellent. Behold it in this.</p>
            <p>The Souldiers of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> plotted with ſome of the <hi>French</hi> Garriſon in <hi>Gifon-Caſtle,</hi> neere <hi>San-Seuerino,</hi> to betray the place vnto them: the <hi>French</hi> entertained the motion, and aſſigned an houre, and the manner, for the execution: In the meane while, they acquainted the Gouernour. The <hi>Arragoneſes</hi> came at the time appointed; found a Port open, and enter; they were taken in the trap; ſeuen hundred, part horſe, and part foot, were ſlaine on the place; the reſt were taken priſoners. Thus Stratagem did preuaile againſt Policy: Stratagem and Policie are of great force, and in Warre may be lawfully vſed.</p>
            <p>It is vſuall and allowable by the Law of Armes (ſaith Sir <hi>Robert Dallington</hi>) for a publique and profeſſed enemy to attempt that by ſtratagem, fraud, or ſuborned treachery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir Rob. Dall.</hi> in his <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>horiſme,</hi> chap. 37.</note> which cannot be got by fine force without long time, vttermoſt danger, and extreame charge, for this way the purchaſe is ſooner made and at leſſe rate. Therefore let them vſe all ſtratagems and policies that may be to circumuent and ouerthrow an enemy; let them vpon fit occaſion
<pb facs="tcp:9112:23"/> corrupt the enemies men with money; let them by cunning meanes and fained letters cauſe the enemies Captaines to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; Let them bring the Generall himſelfe into more diſlike, if hee bee diſliked of his Souldiers: So they may bee rid of him by policie, whom they could not be rid of by force. I will ſhew you the euents of all theſe by preſidents.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhewing how to corrupt the Enemies men with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note>
               <hi>Monſieur Trimouille, Monſieur de Ligny,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Iaques Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultio,</hi> being to warre with <hi>Lodowick Sforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan</hi> in the behalfe of <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth the French King, thought with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues there was no quicker way to end the Warre than to corrupt <hi>Lodowicks</hi> Souldiers with money. He had entertained many <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> into pay, and theſe <hi>Swiſſers</hi> were valiant men of their hands, but very couetous, and eaſie to be corrupted with gold: therefore they ſent priuily to the Colonels of the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> profering them great ſummes of money to forſake <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> or to betray him into their hands. They being tickled with theſe proffers, ſtirred all the reſt to mutiny, taking their occaſions that their payes were not performed at the iuſt dayes that were promiſed. The Duke ran to the ſtirre in perſon, bringing forth vnto them all his ſiluer, plate and veſſels, deſiring them to reſt contented but till the money came from <hi>Milan,</hi> yet they would not yeeld, but ſaid they would depart ſuddenly into their Countrey. The Duke not being able neither with prayers, nor with teares, nor by infinite promiſes to pacifie any whit their barbarous diſloyalty, recommended himſelfe wholly vnto them, to the end that at the leaſt they would lead him to a place of ſafety. But becauſe they had contracted with the <hi>French</hi> Captaines,<note place="margin">Guichiardin. lib. <hi>3.</hi> pag <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> to goe their wayes, and not to lead him with them, being not willing to grant vnto his full demand, yet they conſented that he ſhould march away amongſt them, taking the habit of one of their footmen; and ſo, if he were not knowne, to ſaue himſelfe by the helpe of his fortune. The which conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being accepted of him, for a laſt neceſſitie, was not ſufficient for his ſafety: for that marching by direction, through the midſt of the <hi>French</hi> Armie, he was knowne by the diligent eſpiall of ſuch as were aſſigned to that charge; or rather diſcloſed by the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> themſelues, as he marched in a Squadron of Foot, attired and armed in all points as a <hi>Swiſſer,</hi> and was by that meanes made priſoner.<note place="margin">Guichiardin. lib. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> Here you ſee the <hi>French</hi> Piſtolets could doe more than their men at Armes; ouercomming him who ſtiled himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:9112:23"/> the ſonne of Fortune. From theſe acute and politique <hi>French,</hi> we take our next preſident or example by fained letters to cauſe our enemies Captaines to be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Burbon</hi> and <hi>Triuultio</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> his Generals,<note place="margin">The ſecond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, ſhewing how by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning meanes and fained Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wee ſhall cauſe our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to be ſuſpected.</note> being beſieged and very hardly diſtreſſed within <hi>Milan</hi> by the Emperor <hi>Maximilian,</hi> deuiſed this policie to free themſelues: They ſent a ſeruant of <hi>Triuultio's</hi> (who ſpake the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> tongue perfectly well) with fained letters vnto the Captaines of that Nation, then ſeruing in <hi>Maximilians</hi> Campe, thereby to make them to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and doubted; the which fained meſſenger being taken by the Sentinels and Watches, cunningly (like <hi>Sinon</hi> of <hi>Troy</hi>) humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched them his life and pardon, and that he would deliuer them certaine things, which he had to deliuer to the Colonels and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the <hi>Swiſſers:</hi> the which being granted him, hee drew out of his ſhooe the deuiſed letters, which hee carried to cauſe a ſuſpition to grow vpon theſe Captaines: the which being ſeene and read by the Emperor, holding for certaine their contents to be true, and miſtruſting ſome treaſon, as they had before vſed vnto <hi>Lodowicke Sforza,</hi> raiſed preſently his Campe, and withdrew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with leſſe conſtancie and credit, then to his honour and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was conuenient.</p>
            <p>Here was a way made without a golden bridge: Here was a fetch fit for a <hi>Carthaginian Haniball:</hi> from whom we take the laſt preſident or example, how to bring our enemies Generall into fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſlike, by adding fuell to the former fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haniball</hi> being in <hi>Italy</hi> did ſuch hurt to the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The third ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſhewing how to bring a Generall into further diſlike then he was in before.</note> as they were almoſt at their wits end, not knowing what to doe, nor what Conſull to chooſe: at length they ſent againſt him <hi>Quintus Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Maximus,</hi> who was both their Dictator and Generall; one both skilfull and politique, and by delay meant to prolong the Warre, ſo to haue wearied <hi>Hanibals</hi> ſtrength and power out (for hauing increaſed his pouerty by his long ſtay, ſpending his owne ſtocke, he ſhould at laſt haue beene forced of his owne accord to haue forſaken <hi>Italy,</hi> to the great glory of this man,) who by policy and wiſdome, might haue beene ſaid to haue ouerthrowne <hi>Hani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball;</hi> for this he was deſpiſed of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and counted a cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and confronted by them: But <hi>Haniball</hi> moſt of all feared him, and therefore craftily put this tricke vpon him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:24"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anibals</hi> crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe againſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abius.</hi>
               </note>Hee commanded his Souldiers, when they came neere any of <hi>Fabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> lands, that they ſhould burne and deſtroy all round about them, but gaue them charge in no wiſe to meddle with <hi>Fabius</hi> lands, nor any thing of his, and did purpoſely appoint a Garriſon to ſee that nothing of <hi>Fabius</hi> ſhould miſcarry nor take hurt. This was ſtreight carried to <hi>Rome,</hi> which did wonderfully incenſe the people againſt him, by the meanes of <hi>Metellus</hi> their <hi>Tribune,</hi> who made them an Oration, in which he taxed him no more of Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardlineſſe, but of flat Treaſon, accuſing the Nobility and greateſt men of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying, that from the firſt beginning, they had laid a plot to draw theſe Warres out at length, only to deſtroy the Peoples power and authority, hauing brought the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale into the ſtate of a Monarchy, and into the hands of a priuate perſon, who by his remiſneſſe and delayes, would giue <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi> leiſure to plant himſelfe in <hi>Italy,</hi> and in time giue open paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> at their pleaſure, to ſend <hi>Haniball</hi> a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond aide and Armie, and to make a full conqueſt of all <hi>Italy:</hi> perſwading the people therefore to take the Tyrannicall power of Dictatorſhip from him, and to put their affaires into the hands of <hi>Minutius</hi> Generall of their Horſemen, who would and could tell how to bring them ſafely to paſſe: The people were tickled mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellouſly with theſe ſeditious words, but yet they durſt not force <hi>Fabius</hi> to reſigne his Dictatorſhip,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Fabius</hi> the Dictator.</note> though they bare him a great grudge, and were angry with him in their hearts: Howbeit they ordained, that <hi>Minutius</hi> ſhould thenceforth haue equall power and authority with the Dictator in the Warres; a thing that was neuer ſeene nor heard of before. Now ſay; Was not this a braue policie of <hi>Haniball</hi> to bring <hi>Fabius</hi> into ſuch diſlike at <hi>Rome?</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe into ſuch an vprore vpon it? Surely it was: and it had as good ſucceſſe as might be. Therefore hauing ſufficient pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents for theſe things, feare not to put them in execution, when you ſee fit time. I conclude now as I began, that all theſe policies and more, are to be attained with learning, and often reading of Hiſtories, as by all braue Commanders which euer were yet, may well be vnderſtood. And therefore let no man thinke but a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ought to be learned and read, the which ioyned with experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, makes him a perfect man of Warre, and without this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and reading, a Souldier may haunt the Warres many yeeres,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:24"/> and neuer attaine to the deepe points of Souldiery;<note place="margin">In <hi>Barrets</hi> art of Warre <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 173.</note> the which by much reading and few yeeres of experience, may be farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfected, as may be ſeene by <hi>Lucullus</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and many others of other Nations.</p>
            <p>Thus much of Policie, and of the qualities which befits Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall men.</p>
            <p>The next eight Chapters following declares the vſe of Facing, the vſe of Wheeling, the vſe of Counter-marching, the vſe of Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, the vſe of thoſe Diſtances which are to be obſerued in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, (naturally ariſing out of Doubling) with the words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for either.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of the vſe of Facing.</head>
            <p>IN exerciſe we commonly prefix vnto our ſelues this method or order. Firſt to face and ſtand: Secondly, to face and march.</p>
            <p>When we face and ſtand,<note place="margin">☜ Of facing and ſtanding.</note> it is to ſhew our Souldiers how they ſhould defend themſelues, if they ſhould be ſet vpon, in Front, in Reare, in Flankes: by transferring their faces that way to receiue them cloſing, or ſering themſelues together at a conuenient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and bearing out a<note n="a" place="margin">This is liuely expreſſed in the Hollow battell called <hi>Plaeſium,</hi> wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Musketier are in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, the Pikes outwardly Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted euery way and chargin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ouer-hand to ſhelter the Musketiers. <hi>Apian</hi> in the Warres of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Bingham.</hi>
               </note> multitude of Pikes euery way vpon them: (as that Phalange of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great did) when <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Scipio's</hi> Lieutenant encompaſſed it round with horſe-men and light armed. I cannot doe amiſſe in relating the manner of it vnto you, it being ſo pertinent for my purpoſe, and ſo fit for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the motion: Therefore out of <hi>Apian</hi> I will dilate it thus.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as the horſe and chariots, of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> were put to flight by the <hi>Romane</hi> Horſe-men, and by <hi>Eumenes</hi> his Phalange of foot being deſtitute of horſe, firſt opened and receiued the light armed (that had all the while fought in the Front) into the middeſt of it. Then afterwards againe cloſed: And when <hi>Domitius, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio's</hi> Lieutenant incompaſſed it about with horſe and light armed, which he might eaſily doe, by reaſon it was thruſt vp in a thicke<note n="*" place="margin">This <hi>Plinth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um</hi> was a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſquare battell full of men, and not the hollow <hi>Plinthium</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nophon.</hi> The depth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this <hi>Plinthium</hi> was 32. in depth. The light armed in the middeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Plinthium,</hi> it was driuen to great diſtreſſe: being neither able to
<pb facs="tcp:9112:25"/> charge the enemie, nor yet to countermarch in ſo great a depth as it carried: It grieued them much that their long experience nothing auailed them to annoy the enemy, and that notwithſtanding, they were ſubiect to Arrowes and Darts at all hands. Yet bearing out a multitude of Pikes on euery ſide of their ſquare, they called the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> to come to handle blowes, and ſtill made a countenance, as though they meant to charge, keeping themſelues for all that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Rankes, as being foot-men and heauy armed, and the rather becauſe they had to doe with an Enemy on horſe-backe. Beſides, they were loath to breake the thickneſſe of their battell; which forme they could not now alter. The <hi>Romanes</hi> alſo Durſt not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them, and come to ſword, fearing their experience in War, and cloſeneſſe of Aray, and deſperation. But running about here and there, plyed them with Arrowes and Darts, whereof none was throwne in vaine, falling amongſt a troupe ſo cloſely put together, that they could neither auoid, and decline any thing throwne, nor giue a way, albeit they ſaw it comming. At laſt being weary and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolute what to doe, they retired eaſily, with a threatning counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance notwithſtanding and in good order, and not deliuering the <hi>Romanes</hi> of feare, who durſt not yet come neare, but ſought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy them aloofe; till the Elephants placed in the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lange, being affrighted, and not to be ruled by their gouernours, troubled all, and gaue occaſion of flight. Hitherto <hi>Appian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby you may ſee how ſuddenly they did face, maintaining a Charge (as it were) vpon a ſtand; and when the <hi>Romanes</hi> would not come to handy ſtrokes with them, they angerly, yet leaſurely retreated: and when they were diſtreſſed, made as though they would charge, holding out a multitude of Pikes euery way; to the amazement of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> who durſt not approach them. The like may be done by our<note n="c" place="margin">That is the Hollow ſquare whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Pikes are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and the Musketiers within.</note> Battell, if it ſhould be charged as that was. Thus much to face ane ſtand.</p>
            <p>Now to face and march.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞ Off facing and Marching.</note>When we face and march, it is to ſhew our Souldiers how we can vpon deliberation (as occaſion ſerues) preuent the enemie from Falling on our right or left Wing, by bringing it to ſome Riuer, or ſuch like place of ſtrength for ſuccour, wherby the enemy can haue no way to enco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe it: which we do by bidding them firſt to face, then to march to the place, afterwards to face againe. And ſo they are reduced to the firſt poſture, and the Front is, as it was at the firſt.
<pb facs="tcp:9112:25"/> This we continually vſe in our Trainings at home, to make ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men fit for it in the face of the Enemie. Howſoeuer ſome may be ignorant in the vſe of the motion, yet they cannot bee vnskilfull in the motion it ſelfe, by reaſon of the practiſe. No Battell can well be without this motion, eſpecially in the field, where the enemy doth ſeeke aduantage. Let me therefore ſhew you ſome other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vſes thereof, that it may bee the beter eſteemed, and the oftner practiſed.</p>
            <p>This motion, as it is performed marching,<note place="margin">The vſe of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, as it is performed marching.</note> is of this ſingular vſe, not onely to giue an aſſault vpon the aduerſe wing of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but to fail any way off from the enemy, and ſuddenly againe to turne vpon him with an euen front to his front; that is, Pikes to his Pikes, Shot to his Shot, whereby he is preuented from falling, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the Flankes, or on the Reare, comming on with one maine Bodie.</p>
            <p>Manie other vſes it hath, as partly this; To<note place="margin">Captaine <hi>Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> in his notes vpon <hi>Aelian cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 25.</note> ſhunne a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ground on which an enemie hath ſtrewed, Calthrops, or laid a ſecret trap, this was found practiſed by <hi>Alexand.</hi> the great, when he fought with <hi>Darius</hi> at <hi>Arbela; Arrian</hi> deſcribes it thus<note n="*" place="margin">Arrian lib. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; Alexand. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith he) <hi>Alexander</hi> hauing imbattelled his Army, to fight with <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> had intelligence, that <hi>Darius</hi> had ſtrewed the ground betwixt the two Armies with Calthrops; hee commanded therefore the right Wing, which himſelfe led, to turne faces to the right hand, and to follow him, to the end to goe round about, and avoid the places that were ſtrewed with Calthropes: <hi>Darius</hi> marching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him to the left hand, diſioyned his troopes of horſe, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> taking the aduantage, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing in quickly betwixt the ſpaces, put <hi>Darius</hi> to flight.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee the euent of it, and what a victory <hi>Alexander</hi> gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby. If he had faced and ſtood ſtill, what would it auailed him? Had hee marched fore-right, hee had falne vpon the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropes, but by facing and then marching vpon it, hee effected all.</p>
            <p>Firſt he auoided the ground where the Calthropes lay (by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and marching forth) then hee reduced them againe to their firſt poſture, by facing them to the left hand. Afterwards (taking his aduantage) hee went on to the charge, and ſo defeated the enemie.</p>
            <p>Why <hi>Alexander</hi> made choice (onely) of this motion, is not to be wondred at, becauſe neceſſity made him to make vſe of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:9112:26"/> when no other would ſerue.</p>
            <p>Countermarch had bin ridiculous, ſo had doubling; wheeling had bin in vaine: nay, it was impoſſible for him to haue wheeled, the ground being ſo ſcantie, (betweene him and the Calthropes) his Phalange of ſo great a bredth, and the enemie ſo nigh. Yet ſay he had wheeled (hauing had ground ſufficient) hee muſt haue beene forced (hauing wheeled) to haue faced withall, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched further out, then wheeled againe, or elſe to no purpoſe; ſo haue failed of his expedition.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how fit this motion ſerued <hi>Alexanders</hi> turne, and by it may learne to make like vſe of it, vpon like occaſion.</p>
            <p>Another ſingular vſe of this motion is, to get the vpper ground from the enemie.</p>
            <p>This was found practized by <hi>Philopaemen,</hi> the <hi>Achaean</hi> Generall. When <hi>Machanidas,</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Tirant, had put his left wing to flight, yet he by this meanes reſtored the battell, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obtained the victory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polibius lib.</hi> 11. 634</note>
               <hi>Polibius</hi> deſcribes the manner of it thus;</p>
            <p>The fight being begunne betweene <hi>Machanidas,</hi> the Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monian Tirant, and <hi>Philopaemen,</hi> the Achaean Generall, it happened that <hi>Machanidas</hi> had the better, for he hauing put the left Wing of the Achaean Mercenaries to flight, followed hard the chaſe; <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopaemen,</hi> as long as there was any hope, endeauored to ſtay his men: when he ſaw them vtterly defeated, hee haſted to the right Wing, and perceiuing the enemy buſie in the chaſe, and the place voide where the fight had bin, commanding the firſt<note n="*" place="margin">A <hi>Merarchy</hi> conſiſteth of 2048 men.</note> Merarchies to turn their faces to the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>and, he led them on with high ſpeed, not yet breaking the order of their imbattelling, and quickly ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing vpon the forſaken ground, hee both cut betwixt them that gaue chaſe, and home, and withall got the aduantage of the vpper ground againſt the left wing of the armed, whereby hee obtained the victorie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> vpon the ſame moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Aelian chap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note>If <hi>Philopaemen</hi> had in this action vſed wheeling of his Battell, which onely was the other motion which would haue ſerued his turne, beſides the troubleſomneſſe of the winding about, he ſhould haue bin forced to haue vſed two wheelings, and ſo failed of the celeritie, which was at time requiſite, faces were turned in a trice, and he made himſelfe maſter of the ground hee deſired, before hee could haue wheeled once his Battell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:26"/>
            <p>Beſides to haue Fac'd and ſtood ſtill, had beene to no purpoſe, but Facing and Marching on was to ſome purpoſe, as you haue heard.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what Facing is;<note place="margin">Of the vſe of Facing in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> How it is the eaſieſt of all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but of no leſſe importance or neceſſitie: How it may be done in a trice, though the Enemy come very ſuddenly vpon vs: Though he encompaſſe both our Wings: Though hee enuiron vs round with Foot and Horſe, yet we may Face vpon him, and make him reſiſtance: How that there is no Battell but hath need of this Motion: So that when we finde our Enemies to encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe our right Wing, wee turne our Faces and Weapons that way to receiue them. To the left, when they come to charge vs on that ſide: If on both ſides, then wee turne Faces halfe to the right, and halfe to the left hand. But being to remoue the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell from any of the Flanks, we cauſe Faces to be turned to that Flanke; ſo we lead on vpon the Enemy, either to aſſault him, or to preuent him where he would aſſault. Which if we cannot doe, we make a ſtand, and ſo receiue him. All this I haue expreſſed fully both by precept and example. Now it remaines that I ſhew you foure other things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by what words of Command it may be done.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in what order.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, with which Legge comming forward.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, how to reduce all this (by way of document or obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation) ſhall be declared in the next Chapter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Obſeruations for Facing; ſhewing the manner how to performe the action; with many other Circumſtances appertaining to the precedent Chapter.</head>
            <p>IN the precedent Chapter, mention was made of <hi>Facing.</hi> In this Chapter are certaine Obſeruations poſitiuely ſet downe for the exact performance thereof.</p>
            <p>They are in number foure.</p>
            <p>The firſt obſeruation is, for the motion of the Legge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:27"/>
            <p>The ſecond for reducement to its firſt Poſture.</p>
            <p>The third for diſtance to grace the Action.</p>
            <p>The fourth for words of Command, either to Face and March; or to Face and Stand; expreſſing their vſe.</p>
            <p>Of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</note>Firſt then obſerue that in Facing vpon a ſtand, the Motion, muſt and ought to be performed with the right Legge; that is, the left Legge muſt ſtand firme: The right muſt either remoue forward, or backward: Forward, when you Face to the left hand; Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when you face to the right hand.</p>
            <p>Be it to the right about, or to the left about, the left Leg ſtands firme; only you moue the foot vpon the heele or toe: But in the March it is to be done,<note place="margin">How to Face Marching.</note> ſometimes with the right Legge, ſometimes with the left Legge: With the right Legge, when it is to the left hand: With the left Legge, when it is to the right hand; for you muſt gaine ground, and not loſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond Obſeruation.</note>In the ſecond place, obſerue or take notice, how to reduce vnto the firſt Poſture. This muſt be thus performed:</p>
            <p>When you Face to the right, returne backe to the left hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to reduce vnto your firſt Poſture.</note>When you Face to the left, returne backe to the right hand.</p>
            <p>Hauing Fac'd about to the right, returne about to the left.</p>
            <p>Hauing Fac'd about to the left, returne about to the right. For ſtill the contrary muſt be done. Obſerue it and forget it not.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</note>In the third place obſerue, or take notice, of the Diſtances ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to Facing.</p>
            <p>Theſe Diſtances are of three ſorts: to wit,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Open Order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cloſe Order.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt for Exerciſe: The two laſt for Seruice.</p>
            <p>No Captaine muſt be ſo abſurd, as to Face vpon an Enemy (in open Order) the Enemy comming to puſh of Pike.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecians</hi> would neuer Face to receiue the Charge of an Enemy, but in their cloſe Order.</p>
            <p>Their cloſe Order, was a foot and a halfe from file to file, and three foot from ranke to ranke.</p>
            <p>This we commonly vſe with Pikes. But our Musketiers are neuer to be cloſer then the ſecond Diſtance of three foot in ſquare, becauſe they are to haue a free vſe of their Armes. If then they be at a cloſer Diſtance, they will much throng and trouble one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and are ſubiect to firing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:27"/>
            <p>In the laſt place, obſerue how to giue the words of Command,<note place="margin">The fourth Obſeruation.</note> either to Face and March, or to Face and ſtand. That you may doe it orderly, and properly, I haue fitted them to your mouth thus:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Face to the right hand, March.<note place="margin">Words of Command to Face and March.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Face to the left hand, March.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Face to the right hand about, March.</l>
                     <l>Face to the left hand about, March.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you may ſet vpon your Enemy as you ſee aduantage, or preuent him where he would charge you to your diſaduantage, or ſhun a dangerous ground prepared for you, as <hi>Alexander</hi> did, when <hi>Darius</hi> would haue intrapped him. Thus much to Face &amp; March, and of the words of Command for it.</p>
            <p>Now to face and ſtand, with the words of Command for that Motion.</p>
            <p>The words of proper direction for it are theſe.<note place="margin">Words of Command to Face &amp; ſtand.</note>
            </p>
            <q>Face to the right hand.<note n="*" place="margin">If you reſtore to the firſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, you are to ſay, <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>Thus if the Enemy haue encompaſſed your right Flanke, you are ready for him.</p>
            <q>Face to the left hand.</q>
            <p>Thus if the Enemy haue encompaſſed your left Flanke, you are ready for him.</p>
            <q>Face to the right and left hand, by diuiſion.</q>
            <p>Thus if the Enemy hath encompaſſed both the Wings of your Battell, (being vnable to auoide it<note n="*" place="margin">They face to the right and left, by diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>) you Face thus to reſiſt him.</p>
            <q>Face to the right and about.</q>
            <p>Thus if the Enemy haue ſuddenly made his Approach vpon your Reare, you are ready for him, and reſiſt him in an inſtant.</p>
            <q>Middle men to the right hand about.</q>
            <p>This forme is called <hi>Phalange Amphiſtomus,</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Aelian chap.</hi> 38. And is of excellent vſe to reſiſt the charge of the Enemy, aſſaulting vs in Front and Reare.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:28"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerue the forme of this Face, being ten in depth. This is the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inthium</hi> full of men.</note>The three laſt Rankes face about to the Right.</l>
               <l>The three firſt Rankes in the Front ſtand as you doe.</l>
               <l>The Reſt in the midst to the Right and Left, by diuiſion.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus if the Enemy haue enuironed you about on all ſides: On all ſides you are ready to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Paulus Aemilius.</hi>
               </note>This was the laſt remedy of the <hi>Macedonian Phalange</hi> oppoſed againſt <hi>Paulus Aemylius</hi> in his Battell with <hi>Perſeus,</hi> which diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and had gained the victory, had it not beene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for want of ground.</p>
            <p>Thus much for Facing.</p>
            <p>Now if in ſtead of Facing, you would command Charging, giue the words thus:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Charge to the right hand.</l>
                     <l>Charge to the left hand.</l>
                     <l>Charge both to the right and left hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Charge to the Front.</l>
                     <l>Charge to the Reare.</l>
                     <l>Charge both Front and Reare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Charge euery way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Caution.</note>When you charge vpon a ſtand, fall backe with the right Legg.</p>
            <p>When you charge to goe on, come forward with the left Legg.</p>
            <p>This is to charge Marching.</p>
            <p>Thus much for this Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of the vſe of Wheeling.</head>
            <p>WHeeling is of the ſame vſe with Facing, both may be done vpon the ſudden approach of the Enemy, whether hee ſhew himſelfe on the right or left Flanke, or in the Reare of your Battell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The excellency of Wheeling.</note>If he ſhew himſelfe in the right or left Flanke, Wheeling will
<pb facs="tcp:9112:28"/> haue the preheminence of Facing, for it will oppoſe him with thy front, which are thy beſt men.</p>
            <p>If he ſhew himſelfe in the Reare, Wheeling will yet haue the preheminence, and oppoſe him there with thy fileleaders (or beſt men) as it did before in the Flanke</p>
            <p>But<note n="*" place="margin">Of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemincie of Facing ouer Wheeling.</note> if the enemie ſhew himſelfe in Front and Reare, or in more then theſe places at once (ſuddenly to charge thee) Facing will then haue the preheminence, and Wheeling will doe more harme then good. Therefore being in this ſtraight, the beſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is to turne faces and ſo receiue him.</p>
            <p>But hauing ſufficient place, and fit occaſion to wheele,<note place="margin">Captaine <hi>Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in his notes vpon <hi>Aelian, Chapt.</hi> 25.</note> omit not this oportunitie, but meet him with thy beſt men. For example whereof I bring the <hi>Graetians:</hi> They coveting alwaies to bring their beſt men, that is, the fileleaders to fight; did thus,</p>
            <p>In open order they choſe to countermarch?</p>
            <p>In cloſe order hauing place to wheele their battell about, they did turne the face of it againſt the enemie. If they could doe neither of theſe, they came to the laſt remedie which was turning of faces of euery particular man in the battell. This was the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> order, which ſhewes the excellencie of their diſcipline: And therefore we are willing to follow them, being the Mirrours of Arts and Armes. They were ſo perfect in theſe motions by their continuall practiſe and exerciſe, that few or none were euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable vnto them.</p>
            <p>In wheeling they would moue as a ſhip (or ſome other body) caried about wholly and ioyntly together, remaining vndiſolued.</p>
            <p>When they were to wheele to the right, they did firſt warne the right corner file leader to ſtand ſtill (as it were the hooke of a doore-hinge) and the reſt they commanded altogether to proceed forward, and to turne about the ſame fileleader like the doore.<note n="*" place="margin">They will not wheele, vnleſſe they be at an vnfitting order Pouldion to Houldion and then Rankes to the ſwords point a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance not fit for that moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was the battell wholy turned by them (as the body of a man) to the right, to the left, or about to either, being caried about the corner fileleader, as about a Center. This was a comely ſight to looke vpon? would to God all would doe it as exactly as they But wiſhes are in vaine, men will doe as they liſt, not as they ſhould: <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Some will neither obſerue the diſtance vſed by the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> no the diſtance appointed by our Tacticks, for the comely grace thereof. This diſtance is three foot from file to file, and three foot from ranke to ranke?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:29"/>
            <p>If this be not obſerued, the motion will want grace, the vſe of it will be fruſtrated? the enemie will preuaile againſt them: For how can thoſe men fight whoſe hands are tyed, being thronged and peſtred together, they are as it were bound and tyed, and can neither aſſault the enemie, nor defend themſelues, but are ſubiect to be killed one of another. Therefore true diſtances, muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. But of diſtances more hereafter. Faceing and wheeling are the ſubiects on which I treat.</p>
            <p>Now faceing and wheeling being ioyned together are of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vſe? To preuent the enemie where he would aſſault you: To giue the aſſault on him, and to circumuent him in taking of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of ground, Wind and Sunne, it likewiſe ſerues to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the middeſt of your battell with the beſt men. By Wheeling the Wings into the middeſt of the battell. In doing whereof you curtall the depth, and extend the length, bringing more men to fight then you had before</p>
            <p>Thus much of Wheeleing. The words of Command followes in the next chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of the words of command for <hi>Wheeling.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe words of command for Wheeling may be thus giuen.</p>
            <q>Viz. Wheele the body to the right hand.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vſe.</note>Thus if the enemie appeare to the right Flanke, you bring your beſt men to fight againſt him:</p>
            <q>Wheele the body to the left hand.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vſe.</note>Thus if the enemy come to charge your left Flanke, you bring your beſt men againſt him:
<q>Wheele the body about to the right hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vſe.</note>Thus if the enemie appeare in the Reare, you bring your File-leaders, that is, your beſt men to fight.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:29"/>Wheele the body about to the left hand.</q>
            <p>Thus you are reduced to your firſt Poſture.<note place="margin">The Vſe</note>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be you would Face, then march; after Face againe, then wheele. If you would, it may be commanded thus:
<q>
                  <l>Face to the right hand.<note place="margin">Face &amp; March.</note> and march twenty paces.</l>
                  <l>Face to the left hand. and march twenty paces.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Then wheele to the left, and charge ouer-hand.</p>
            <p>Thus you may gaine the aduantage of ground vpon the right Flanke:<note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> you may aſſault your enemy on the left Wing with your File-leaders or Front, you may gaine the aduantage of Wind and Sunne, from the enemie: And preſently fall vpon a charge.</p>
            <p>It may be you would extend the length of your Battell by whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (by bringing the Wings into the midſt.) Then you may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thus.</p>
            <q>Wheele the Wings into the middeſt of the Battell. Face to your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander.</q>
            <p>Thus the ſtrength of your Battell lies in the middeſt;<note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> it may be you would reduce. Then command thus:
<q>To the right hand about.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then begin with the Bringers vp, and ſay:
<q>Wheele your Wings againe into the middeſt of the Battell.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then bid them Face to their Commander: after that.</p>
            <q>Face to the left hand about.</q>
            <p>And ſo they are fully reduced as they were.</p>
            <p>It may bee you would know the way how to performe this Wheeling, for as yet you are Ignorant. Then obſerue how to do it by this Inſtance which will ſomewhat explaine it vnto you.</p>
            <p>There be ten File-leaders in Front,<note place="margin">The Inſtance.</note> fiue of them on the right Wing wheeles forward to the left, transferring their faces to the contrary Wing, their Followers mouing with them, and ſtanding behinde them as they did at the firſt, only they change their former ground, as did the File-leaders.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:30"/>
            <p>The other fiue on the left Wing wheeles forward to the right, meeting them in the midſt, face to face, hauing all their Followers (behind them) as the other fiue. Then the Commander bids them Face to him: And ſo the countenances of all the Souldiers are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (or transferred) all one way. Thus you may performe this wheeling; but action doth better performe it than words.</p>
            <p>This wheeling of the Wings into the midſt of the Battalia, was vſed by the Ancient <hi>Grecians,</hi> to make their <hi>Diphalange Antiſtomus,</hi> their <hi>Diphalange Periſtomus,</hi> their <hi>Hollow-wedge.</hi> The Figure of which is to be ſeene in <hi>Aelian,</hi> with the deſcription of them, Chap. 36. 40. and 41.</p>
            <p>What Victories haue beene gained by this kinde of Imbattal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I haue ſeen, and read in a written Copie of Captain <hi>Binghams</hi> compoſing, to be diuulged (ſhortly) for a publike good, that is now but for a priuate vſe. This worthy Captaine was the man that did firſt ſhew the Gentlemen of the Artillery Garden how they ſhould performe this kinde of wheeling, which now they doe moſt exactly: And he will proue the vſe of it to be as profitable for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice now, as heretofore with the <hi>Grecians,</hi> if we will but doe what he ſhall aduiſe. Thus much of this Kinde of Wheeling, and of the other Wheeling, which muſt not be vſed when the enemy is vpon you, but when he is aloofe off. Now of Counter-march.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of Counter-marches, and the diuers kindes thereof: with the manner how they are to be made, and of their vſe.</head>
            <p>COunter-marches are two-fold: for either we Counter-march the Files or the Rankes. And theſe either by changing of ground, or keeping ſtill the ſame ground.</p>
            <p>If we Counter march by Files, it is to oppoſe the enemie appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Reare with our beſt men. If by Rankes, it is to bring one Wing into the place of the other; or all our beſt men into the middeſt of the Battell.</p>
            <p>If we Counter-march by Files or Rankes, to change our ground,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:30"/> we do it either by the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<note n="a" place="margin">The modern Counter-march ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is thus performed; The Fyle-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders counter-march to the right, the next Ranke ſtands til they be paſt, then they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: the like do all the reſt, transferring themſelues to a new ground.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Counter-march which was inuented for that purpoſe, and to be performed ſtanding.</p>
            <p>If to maintaine ground, then we doe it by the Choraean Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-march, which makes the File-leaders to take the ground of the Bringers vp, and the Bringers vp the ſame ground, in the which the File-leaders ſtood. The like in the Wings.</p>
            <p>Theſe Counter-marches, namely, the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monian,</hi> and the <hi>Choraean,</hi> are deſcribed by <hi>Aelian</hi> thus.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aelian chap.</hi> 20 of the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Crunter-march by Fyle.</note> by File, is ſaid to be, when the File-leader turneth about his face, &amp; all the reſt with the Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger-vp goeth againſt him on the right or left hand, and paſſing on to the ground before the Front of the Battell; place themſelues in order one after another, according as the File-leader himſelfe hath turned his face.</p>
            <p>This Counter-march you ſee transferreth the whole File to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place equall to the firſt, by taking the ground that lyeth before the Front, in lieu of that it loſt behinde. It likewiſe maketh Shew to the enemy appearing in the Reare of running away, but it is of excellent vſe.</p>
            <p>Say that before thy Battell lay a Riuer,<note place="margin">The vſe of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march by Fyle.</note> and betweene the Riuer and thee a faire plot of ground, higher than that thou ſtandeſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (the enemy appearing in the Reare, and compelling thee to fight) the only way to oppoſe him with the beſt men, and to got this ground for thy aduantage, is this <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march. This Counter-march was firſt Inuented by <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Father of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Counter-march by Fyle is,<note place="margin">Of the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monian</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-march by Fyle, deſcribed by <hi>Aelian, chap.</hi> 28.</note> when the Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vp turneth his face about, and all the reſt turning alſo their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and proceeding forward together with their Fyle-leader, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelues proportionably in the ground which was behind the reare of the Battell.</p>
            <p>Or elſe, when the Bringer-vp turneth his face about, and hee that ſtood next before him paſſiing by on the right or left hand, is placed againe next before him, and the reſt following, are placed one before another in their former order, till the Fyle-leader bee firſt.</p>
            <p>In this Counter-march you ſee, the proceeding is contrary to the former that tooke the ground before the Phalange, or Battell,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:31"/> this takes the ground after. In that the moouing was from the reare to the front; in this from the front to the reare.<note n="*" place="margin">Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi> in his notes vpon <hi>Aelian chap.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Aelian</hi> preferreth the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Counter-march before the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> becauſe in it the Soldiers ſeeme to fall on and charge, wherin the <hi>Macedonian</hi> they ſeeme to flie. There is notwithſtanding, times (as Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi> notes) when it is better to vſe the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian;</hi> As when you ſeeke to gaine ſome ground of aduantage: or in caſe you mean to march on and not to fight with the Enemy, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you be compelled, for the <hi>Macedonian</hi> continueth ſtill the march, and ſtaieth not: the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> returneth vpon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and ſo looſeth ground in marching.</p>
            <p>There is likewiſe times (ſay I) when it is more requiſite to vſe this <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Counter-march, than any other.</p>
            <p>As in caſe you haue paſſed the ground which the enemy follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeekes to gaine, and to charge you ſuddenly, the onely way to poſſeſſe it againe, and to fight with him with your beſt men, is thus to Counter-march; the <hi>Macedonian</hi> here will doe no good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian chap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note>The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> haue another Counter-march, which bears the name, and that is this; the Fyle-leaders begin the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march, and euery one in their Files follow them orderly. This is no other then our modern Counter-march now in vſe.</p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Of the <hi>Chorae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Counter-march by Fyle, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Perſian</hi> or <hi>Cretan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Choraean</hi> Counter-march by Fyle, is ſaid to be, when the Fyle-leader turning about to the right hand, precedeth the Fyle, and all the reſt follow, till the Fyle-leader haue the place of the Bringer-vp, and the Bringer-vp the place of the Fyle-leader. This Counter-march (ſaith <hi>Aelian</hi>) is called likewiſe <hi>Perſian</hi> &amp; <hi>Cretan: Perſian</hi> and <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etan</hi> (ſaith Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi>) becauſe it was vſed among the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Cretans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Captaine <hi>Bing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in his notes vpon <hi>Aelian chap.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Choraean</hi> alſo, for the ſimilitude it had with the ſolelmne <hi>Grecian</hi> daunces vpon Stages, the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſhewed themſelues in ſuch daunces being called <hi>Chorus,</hi> who in their daunces ordered themſelues into ſyles and rankes, as Souldiers doe in battell, and moouing themſelues to the brinke of the Stage, when being ſtraightned by the place, they could paſſe no further, they retired one through the rankes of the other, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not the bounds of the place, as is done in this Counter-march:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The words of command for the <hi>Choraean</hi> Cuunter-march by Fyle.</note>It may be commanded thus;
<q>Fyle-leaders, Counter-march to the place of the Bringers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vp, and ſtand, and let your Files follow you, keeping your diſtance.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:31"/>
            <p>Or thus;
<q>Fyles, Counter-march, and maintaine ground.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> may be commanded thus;
<q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The words of command for the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Counter-march by File deliuered in Captaine <hi>Binghams</hi> owne words.</note>Bringers-vp, turne your faces about to the right hand: the reſt, turne your faces about, and beginning at them that are next the Bringers-vp, Counter-march, and place your ſelues in your diſtances, before the Bringers-vp, and one before another, till the Fyle-leader be firſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or thus;
<q>Face all to the Reare: Bringers-vp ſtand; the next Ranke, paſſe through by their right hand, and place your ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, keeping your diſtances; all the reſt moue with them, placing your ſelues one before another till the Fyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader be firſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When your men are perfects you need but ſay, <hi>The Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Counter-march,</hi> and it is enough.</p>
            <p>This gaines the ground lying after the Reare, as the <hi>Macedonian</hi> the groundlying before the Front: Now the <hi>Macedonian</hi> may be thus commanded;
<q>File-leaders, turne your faces about to the right hand;<note place="margin">Words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march by File, <hi>Aelian. chap.</hi> 28.</note> the reſt of euery Fyle paſſe through in order, one after another, and place your ſelues at your diſtances, after your Leaders, turning your faces about, and ſo ſtand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Looke what theſe Counter-marches doe by Fyle, the very ſame they doe by Ranke for like aduantage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march by Ranke, taketh the ground that lyeth on the ſide of the contrarie Wing, beginning to moue at the corner of the Wing which is neareſt the enemie, ſeeming ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to him to runne away, becauſe it diſmarcheth from him, as that of the Fyle did before.</p>
            <p>The words of command for it may be theſe;
<q>The right hand corner File face to the left;<note place="margin">Words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Counter-march by Rank</note> the reſt of each File paſſe through to the left, and place your ſelues orderly behind your ſide-men, keeping your diſtance.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:33"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>This gaineth the ground lying on the ſide of the right Wing, fartheſt of from the Enemy. The Enemy appeared to the left Wing B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Counter march you may ſet the ſtrongeſt part of your Battell againſt the Enemy, and apply the weakeſt vnto ſome Riuer L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, Hill, or ſuch like place, ſo that the Enemy cannot come to encomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian countermarch by ranke.</note>The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Counter-march by Ranke, taketh the ground that lieth on the ſide of that Wing which is towards the Enemy, and bringeth the beſt Wing to be formoſt againſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, comming ſtill on vpon him, without any ſhew of running away; and by theſe words of command may be effected;
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Words of command for the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Counter-march by ranke. <hi>The vſe.</hi>
                  </note>Left hand corner File, where the Enemy appeareth, turne your faces to the left hand; the reſt of each Ranke, turne your faces, and paſſe thorow to the left hand, and place your ſelues before your ſide-men, keeping your diſtances.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus when our forces are able to encounter the enemy, and we deſire to bring our beſt wings to fight; then we proceed after this manner to oppoſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Chorae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march by ranke.</note>The Choraean Countermarch by ranke keepeth the ſame ground the battell had at firſt, and bringeth one Wing, into the place of the other, or elſe the Sections to poſſeſſe the place of the Wings, thereby to ſtrengthen the midſt of the battell. Theſe two may be effected, as the other, by ſeuerall words of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</p>
            <p>The firſt by this word of command,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the Choraean Countermarch by ranke.</note>Rankes to the right hand Countermarch and maintaine ground.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond by this word of command,
<q>Countermarch the Wings into the midſt of the battell.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The way to doe it is this,</p>
            <p>Firſt they are to face to the right and left hand by diuiſion: Then to Countermarch into the midſt of the battell; After they are to face to their Commander, and ſo the Countermarch is effected.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>Thus we ſtrengthen the midſt of our battell with our beſt men; bringing them to fight with the enemie, which is the end of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termarch. Wherein notwithſtanding there is a Caution to bee
<pb facs="tcp:9112:33"/> held, that if the enemie be very neare, that we cannot conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Countermarch, before he come vpon vs, we forbeare, leſt we fall into diſorder, and in diſorder be eaſily defeated. In which caſe the beſt remedie is to turne faces and ſo receiue him.</p>
            <p>As Countermarches are not to be done, vnleſſe the enemie be aloofe off, ſo neither can they well be done but at open order.</p>
            <p>When then your files and rankes are at ſix foot, which is (your firſt diſtance) Then you haue ſufficient roome to Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march any way.</p>
            <p>But in Countermarch obſerue this.</p>
            <p>If the word be for the right hand, then ſtep forth with the right legge, and bring the left legge ouer.</p>
            <p>If to the left, then ſtep forth with the left legge, and bring the right ouer.</p>
            <p>But if the Word be to the right, and maintaine ground, then ſtand faſt with the right legge, and bring the left ouer. Thus much of Countermarching.</p>
            <p>Now of Doubling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the vſe of Doubling.</head>
            <p>THere is two kinde of Doubling, the one of Rankes, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. The firſt doth double the<note n="a" place="margin">The length of the batell is the Ranke, the depth is the File Rankes ſtretch forth in length, Files in depth (ſaith <hi>Suidas.</hi>)</note> Length, the ſecond the Depth of your battell.</p>
            <p>The Length of your battell may bee doubled in Place or Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>In<note n="b" place="margin">Doubling of the length of a battell in place.</note> place, when euery file doth open, from three foot to ſix foot, which is your open order in files. By this meanes the Front poſſeſſeth double ground to that it had before. There is another way to double the Front in place, as you ſhall heare anon.</p>
            <p>The Length of your battell is<note n="c" place="margin">Doubling of the length of a battell in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> doubled in Number, when of twentie in a ranke, it is made fortie, and of fortie foureſcore. So that you haue twice as many men in the Front as you had before.</p>
            <p>This doubling of the Length of your battell by number, may be done vpon fit occaſion, either in open order, or in order</p>
            <p>In open order, by doubling of Rankes, by middle men doing
<pb facs="tcp:9112:34"/> the ſame. By bringers vp doubling the front either to the right or left hand at diſcretion. In order by middle men doubling of the Front, either to the right or left hand intire, or by deuiſſion to both. Which doth likewiſe double the length of a Battell, not onely in number but in place alſo, as Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi> doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in his notes upon <hi>Aelian</hi> chap. 29.<note place="margin">Chap. 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Two Cauſes are aſſigned for the doubling of the length of your Battell both in number and place. The one to ouerwing the enemie. The other to auoid ouerwinging.</p>
            <p>Two wayes you may auoid ouerwinging.</p>
            <p>One is by making choiſe of ſuch a ground, as may giue you this aduantage of the enemie; That he can neuer compaſſe you in behinde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the liues of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> and <hi>S lla,</hi> pag. 630. &amp; 478.</note> nor flanke you on the ſides. Now if you cannot finde ſuch a ground, vſe art. Caſt a trench vpon each flanke; or Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons on either Wing. As <hi>Syila</hi> and <hi>Huniades</hi> did, fearing to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed by the multitude of their enemies.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way to auoid ouerwinging is, by placing of Aides in the Reare of your Battell; or by laying them in Ambuſh aloofe off, that ſo vpon a word giuen they may ſuddenly ſtart out vpon the Enemy, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> made his to doe at the Battell of <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> where he put <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great to flight. Theſe Aides muſt be of the moſt chiefeſt Souldiers you haue, with Officers appointed for their conduct, as was vſed by the auntient <hi>Romanes</hi> before and in <hi>Vegetius</hi> time,<note place="margin">Vegetius lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> who did alwaies reſ rue many of theſe Aides, when their number was inferior to their Enemies, their Battell leſſe pitched, and they in danger to be ouerwinged. But when they had plenty of fighting men, they by Doubling would make their Battell equall in length and depth to their Enemies. So that they could not breake through or ouerwinge them.</p>
            <p>Thus much to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oid ouerwinging. And for the doubling of the length of a Battell in pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and number.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doubling the depth of a Battell in place.</note>The depth of your Battell is doubled in place, when euery Ranke from the ſwords point opens to three foot, from three foot to ſix foot, from ſix foot to twelue foot, which is your double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The vſe of this is twofold.</p>
            <p>Firſt to imploy a great deale of ground for your owne aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, making your number ſeeme more then it is. Secondly, to make way for the Canon ſhot, by which the enemy afar of would annoy your flanks. Therefore you march at a double diſtance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:34"/>
            <p>The depth of your Battell is doubled by number,<note place="margin">Doubling th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> depth of a Battell by number</note> when of ten in File, it is made twenty, of twenty forty, and of ſorry foureſcore.</p>
            <p>The doubling of the depth of your Battell may be done vpon fit occaſion, either in open order or in cloſe order.</p>
            <p>In open order, by doubling of Files: When Files double by Countermarch, either to the right or left hand: Or when halfe the Rankes double the right or left flanke: When Ranks file by conuerſion, either to the right or left hand, which is vſually done at a double diſtance.</p>
            <p>In order (or cloſe order) by aduancing of Files to the right or left hand: By File-leaders drawing forth their Files (into one) or if you will both to the right and left hand by diuiſion. Then both right and left hand File leads forth together: ſo the body is drawne into two Files.</p>
            <p>All theſe waies and more, may the depth of your Battell be doubled in place and number, not to change the forme thereof, or (if it be) to alter the faſhion, whereby your Battell may bee made ſuteable to the ground vpon any occaſion: which is not the leaſt thing to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p>Obſerue.</p>
            <p>A large fronted Battell is vnfit for a narrow place.</p>
            <p>A deepe narrow Battell for a Champion, is not ſo ſuteable.</p>
            <p>This the <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Grecians</hi> knew full well, and therefore they would order themſelues accordingly, making a politicke vſe of either, as they ſaw occaſion.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Manius Acilius</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Conſul, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fight with <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great in the Straits of <hi>Thermopy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> becauſe therein he could march with his men no more then fiue in Front. He ordered all his Legions into an<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Orthiophala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is a deepe <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lange</hi> commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly called a <hi>Heirſ,</hi> hauing the Depth much excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Length. <hi>Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>an. chap.</hi> 30. <hi>Appian</hi> in the war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes</hi> with <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ians.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Orthiophalanx,</hi> wich was a kinde of Battell in forme of a Heirſe, of far greater depth than length. Thus being extended in depth (and but fiue in Ranke) he proceeded on, appointing <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> (one of his Tribunes) with a ſelected band of men to fetch a compaſſe about to ſeeke ſome other paſſage: If not, to ſcale the Rocks, and then to ſeize vpon <hi>Antiochus</hi> Campe. And likewiſe hee ſent <hi>Lucius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius</hi> (another of his Tribunes) wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a like band of men, to force the <hi>Aet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lians</hi> from the Rocks on the other ſide, (he being to paſſe vnder them) that ſo hauing gained the Rocks, they might further his paſſage, and annoy <hi>Antiochus</hi> from thence wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h
<pb facs="tcp:9112:35"/> miſſiue weapons. He himſelfe led his Army in Front againſt <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> in the manner before ſaid. Now <hi>Antiochus</hi> hauing forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Straits with a wall (where it was broad) ſtood there ready to receiue him with his Battell of <hi>Macedonians,</hi> farre broader in Front than <hi>Acilius</hi> Armie was. But when <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> had gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Hills, <hi>Antiochus</hi> was inſtantly ſtrucke into amazement, and <hi>Acilius</hi> taking courage thereby, came brauely on, and forced <hi>Antiochus</hi> to flight. Thus ſuting his Battell to the nature of the place, (and yet making vſe of his men for his beſt aduantage) he obtained a glorious victory.</p>
            <p>One example more out of <hi>Xenophons</hi> Hiſtorie, and ſo I will conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nophon. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>The <hi>Grecians</hi> which <hi>Cheriſophus</hi> and <hi>Xenophon</hi> conducted out of <hi>Perſia,</hi> were in the Champaigne ordered into a ſquare hollow Battell, euery part of like ſtrength, with their baggage and looſe multitude in the midſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Grecians</hi> when they came into the Country of the <hi>Cardu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans</hi> and <hi>Colchans,</hi> were otherwiſe ordered.</p>
            <p>There was high Hilles, huge ſteepe Mountaines, and but narrow paſſage. They muſt now be Imbattelled (not in a hollow<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeſium</hi> a ſquare bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l of men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollow in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Plaeſium</hi>) but in ſeuerall Companies, and euery Company into a ſingle File, euery file hauing an hundred men a peece, aſcending thoſe ſteepe Mountaines, and beating the enemie from thence, which ſtood thereon in battell aray, doing more with ten thouſand men, than a King of <hi>Perſia</hi> could doe with twelue Myriades, that is, twelue hundred thouſand.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> (Mirrours of Armes and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) did alwaies ſhape their battell according to the proportion of ground, and being perfect in the art of Imbattelling, did all things proper as they ſaw occaſion. The like muſt we. And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the doubling of the Length and Depth of a Phalange or Battell. Now followes the Diſtances to be obſerued in them. So the words of command ſhall follow for all in the fiue and twentieth Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> Of the Diſtances to be obſerued in Battell. And of their vſe.</head>
            <p>DIſorder is the confuſion of a Battell, but good Order p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is confuſion. Therefore all Commanders, as much as in them lies, muſt ſtudie to preuent this in time.</p>
            <p>And this may be done by obſeruing of Diſtance, for Diſtance is the rule that ſquares all. Diſtance is to the battell, as the ſoule to the body. The Battell may be called a body. Now take away Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from this body, and it falls to ruine for want of a ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphicrates</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> ſaid, That in an Armie of men, the light horſe-men reſembled the hands, the men at Armes the feet, the battell of foot-men, the ſtomacke and breſt, and the Captaine the head of the body.</p>
            <p>See here a Millitary body proportioned to the body of a man: See how it receiues motion and life, Diſtance being the ſoule that makes it moue. Care then ought to be had in mouing: now this care is effected by the obſeruing of Diſtances.</p>
            <p>Three kinds of diſtances are mentioned by <hi>Aelian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſhutting of a Phalange or Battell.</p>
            <p>The firſt are large diſtances of foure Cubits, which amount to ſix foot.</p>
            <p>The ſecond are leſſe, but of two Cubits, which amount to three foot.</p>
            <p>The third are of a leſſer kinde, but of a Cubit, which amounteth at the moſt but to a foot and a halfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all one and the ſame, with open Order, Order, and cloſe Order.</p>
            <p>Open Order, is when euery Souldier in the battell taketh ſix foot both in File and Ranke, and marcheth with their Pikes ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. It is for eaſe in marching, being likewiſe of great vſe going againſt a Fort or ſtrong place of the enemies, for it giues way to the Cannon ſhot, and is of ſingular vſe to ſaue your men. We vſe to march thus when the enemy keepes aloofe off.</p>
            <p>Order is when euery ſouldier in battell taketh three foot both in File and Ranke, and marcheth with their Pikes either aduanced or Ported.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:36"/>
            <p>This is to prepare for skirmiſh when the enemie is neare.</p>
            <p>Cloſe Order, is when euery Souldier in the battell taketh a foot and a halfe in File, and a foot a foot and a halfe from the ſwords point, which is three foot in Ranke. And this is to endure the brunt of a Charge.</p>
            <p>The firſt was vſed in Ancient times for march, Solemne pompes and ſhewes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond for their fights only before they did Ioyne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Noted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Capt. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngham</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aelian ch.</hi> 11.</note>The third was the Sinaſpiſme of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therein they Ioyned Target to Target, which they neuer vſed but when either they gaue vpon, or receiued the charge of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The Targets ſo knit together, ſerued for a wall, as it were, to the whole Phalange; and by them the ſouldier was defended from the Miſſiue weapons of the Enemie, and his body couered euen from the piercing of the ſword.</p>
            <p>This was formerly vſed by the Ancient <hi>Heroes</hi> at <hi>Troy,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viued againe to new life, by <hi>Philip,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who firſt conſtituted the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Phalange, and inuented the diſtances of opening and ſhutting the ſame. From his diſcipline (as the learned Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi> obſerues) ſprung theſe diſtances in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aelian chap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> of which I haue ſpoke.</p>
            <p>And thus I haue briefly declared the vſe of thoſe diſtances which are to be obſerued in Battell. The words of command for them may be theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eiles and Rankes, open to ſix foot.</hi> Now they are at open order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rankes and Files, cloſe to three foot.</hi> Now they are at order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files, cloſe to a foot and a halfe.</hi> Now they are at cloſe order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rankes and Flles, to your open order.</hi> That is, ſix foot euery way.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus if your Battell bee diſioyned by too large diſtances, you may reduce it to good order by cloſing. If it be thronged vp, or peſtered too cloſe together, you may amend all by conuenient ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Too much thronging bindeth the Souldiers hands, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the vſe of their weapons; and too farre ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder breaketh the Battell, and maketh a paſſage for the Enemy, whereby he may enter. Therefore theſe three ſorts of diſtances,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:36"/> to wit, open Order, Order, and cloſe Order, haue beene inuented as the onely meanes betweene both, to amend all, and to fit our turne as wee ſee occaſion.</p>
            <p>Thus much for Diſtances, of their vſe, and the words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand giuen for them.</p>
            <p>The words of command for doubling of the length and depth of a Battell next followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> This Chapter ſheweth what the words of Command are, by which the length and depth of a Battell is doubled, either in place or number; and teacheth a young Soldier how to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Motion.</head>
            <p>IN the three and twentieth Chapter of this booke, mention was made of the doubling of the length and depth of a Battell, both in place and number, but the words of command were refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto this Chapter.</p>
            <p>If then you would double the length of your Battell in place, the proper words of direction for it may bee this, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Open your Files from your cloſe order to your open order, ſix foot.</q>
            <p>The manner of the Action is thus performed: The middle Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders preſſe vpon their Flankers, firſt, taking their diſtance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, hauing opened both waies, the reſt of the companie on both Flankes, takes their diſtance from them: now ſixteene men are ſo extended, as they hold as much ground in breadth as would ſerue thirty two men.</p>
            <p>It may be commanded ſome other way, peculiar and diſtinctly from the other: as,<note place="margin">The word of command for doubling the length of a Battell in place</note>
               <q>Files, open to the right hand to your open order, ſix foot.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Files open to the left hand to your open order.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:37"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files open to the right hand</note>The word being giuen to the right hand, the left hand File is not to mooue, but ſtandeth faſt, the next to the left hand Fyle, firſt taketh the diſtance, preſſing vpon the right hand, ſtill opening by the right hand, till they haue taken the diſtance of ſix foot.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files open to the left Hand.</note>The word being giuen to the left hand, the right hand Fyle muſt ſtand faſt, the reſt muſt open to the left hand, ſtill preſſing vpon the left hand Files, till they are all in the diſtance and order com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p>Thus by three diſtinct peculiar words of command, may the length of your Battell be doubled in place, each of which you may make choiſe of as occaſion ſerues.</p>
            <p>But if your Battell beare too great a bredth, by poſſeſſing too much ground, then you may amend it by this word of command, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">The two mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Files cloſe firſt, the reſt mouer with them, both to the right and left hand, to the diſtance named</note>Files, cloſe to your order.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Files, cloſe to the right hand, to your order.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Files, cloſe to the left hand, to your order.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files cloſe,</note>If the words be, <hi>Piles cloſe,</hi> without naming to any hand, then it muſt be performed thus;</p>
            <p>The two middle Leaders muſt cloſe, the one to the left hand, the other to the right hand, till they are in the diſtance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; then the reſt of the companie muſt take their diſtance from them on either Flanke, cloſing to the middle Leaders.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files cloſe to the right hand.</note>If the word be, <hi>To the right hand,</hi> the right hand File moues not, but ſtandeth faſt; all the reſt cloſe to the right hand File, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their diſtance one by another from the right hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files cloſe to the left hand.</note>If the word be, <hi>To the left hand,</hi> obſerue like forme; then the left hand File ſtands faſt, the reſt of the Files cloſe, and take their diſtance from the left hand. Thus much of the words of command, by which the Battell is leſſened or doubled in place,<note place="margin">The words of command for the doubling of the depth of a Battell in place</note> thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying a greater or leſſer bredth, as the word is giuen.</p>
            <p>If you would double the depth of your Battell in place, the proper word of direction for it may be this, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9112:37"/>Open your Rankes from the Front to the Reare, to your open order, ſix foot.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of the Action is thus to be performed; The firſt Ranke muſt ſtand firme: the ſecond Ranke takes their diſtance firſt; all the reſt muſt doe the like diſtinctly in order.</p>
            <p>Now you take as much ground in depth for ten, as would ſerue very well for twenty men.</p>
            <p>If you would double the length of your Battell in number,<note place="margin">The words of command for the doubling of the length of a Battell in number.</note> that is, to make the front haue twice as many Files, or perſons in it as it had before, then you may effect it by this word of command;
<q>Rankes to the right hand, double.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or thus,
<q>Rankes to the left hand double.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is thus performed:</p>
            <p>Euery ſecond Ranke cometh between the diſtance of the Ranke before it, and that either to the right or left hand,<note place="margin">Rankes to the rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hand double.</note> as the word is giuen, ſo that of ten in Ranke, they become twenty in Ranke, and but fiue in depth, who before were ten in depth, becauſe the Front is doubled.</p>
            <p>Or if you are minded to effect it by middle men, then the laſt fiue Rankes muſt march vp through the diſtances betweene the Files, till they come to be euen in Front, with the File-leaders, then they ſtand, hauing euerie one their followers following them, as they had before, onely now they are fiue in depth, when they were before tenne.</p>
            <p>The word of command for it is;
<q>Middle men, to the right hand double your Front.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or, being minded to diuide your middle men, and ſo to double.<note place="margin">Doubling of the length of a Battell by mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle men.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Then the laſt fiue rankes muſt turne their faces, the one halfe in their files to the right hand, and the other halfe to the left hand, and ſo march forth from both the Flankes, till they haue gotten ſuch a proportion of ground, or diſtance, as is anſwerable to the order, the firſt fiue Rankes doe ſtand in: and then preſently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out attending any further commandement, they muſt turne their faces againe towards the front, and march vpon both flankes till
<pb facs="tcp:9112:38"/> they come euen with the front.</p>
            <p>The word of direction is,
<q>Middle men double your front to the right and left hand by diuiſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or, being minded not to diuide your middle men, but to bring them vp to the front, entire to one particular hand. Then the fiue laſt rankes muſt face, then march forth altogether beyond the skirts of the body, then face to the front, and march vp to ioyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in euen front with the file leaders.</p>
            <p>The word of Command to effect it maybe this,
<q>Middle men to the right hand Intire double your front.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or if you are minded after all this, to make vſe of your bringers vp in the front of your battle, then you may performe it, by this word of Command,
<q>Bringers vp to the right hand double your front.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt ranke you know are the bringers vp: Theſe being in the reare doe aduance through the diſtances betweene the files:<note place="margin">The length of a battell dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the bringers vp</note> And next after them the next ranke: and ſo the reſt ſucceſſiuely till the bringers vp be in ranke with the Leaders, and their mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle men with the Leaders middle men. Thus your front is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with your beſt men, being now but fiue in depth, who were before tenne in depth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of the battell in Depth by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note>If you would double the depth of your battell in number, that is, make ſome files haue twice as many men in them as they had before, you may effect it by this word of Command,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>The word of Command for it.</p>
                     <p>Files to the right hand dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  </note>Files to the right hand double.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is thus to be performed.</p>
            <p>The right hand file (which is the outermoſt file, on the right hand moues nor, but ſtands faſt, the next file to the right hand file, moues into the right hand file, ſo that of tenne in depth, it is now become twentie. Accordingly euery ſecond File moueth into their next file on the right hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Files to the left hand double.</note>The like order muſt be obſerued, if the word be to the left hand, the left hand file muſt ſtand faſt, and euery ſecond file is to moue into the next file on their left hand. Thus the depth is doubled by number.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But it may be, you would execute it by Countermarch as did the Macedonians. Then the word of Command is,
<q>Double your files by Countermarch, to the right hand.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aelian</hi> chap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is performed when the next ſide files in ſeuerall (as in the former example the ſecond,<note place="margin">The firſt, thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fift, ſeuenth, ninth, are odd files, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond fourth, ſixth, eigth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tenth, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen files.</note> and the fourth and the reſt of the euen files) Countermarch to the Reare placing themſelues behinde the bringers vp of the odde files, <hi>Aelian</hi> chap. 29.</p>
            <p>It may be you would double the right flanke with the left flanke, to make the Orthiophalanx, or heirſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aelian</hi> chap. 30.</note> battell, which proceedeth by Wing, hauing the depth much exceeding the length.</p>
            <p>The way to doe it is by this word of Command,
<q>Halfe Rankes double to the right hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Rankes double the right flanke.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is thus performed.</p>
            <p>Halfe the Rankes (for they are diuided as it were into two parts) turnes their faces to the right hand, and marches into the ſpaces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the other Rankes, and being within, they face as the reſt: Thus the battell is brought into a Wing.</p>
            <p>It may be you would bring it into a file.</p>
            <p>Then the word of Command may be this,
<q>Rankes file to the right hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Rankes file by Conuerſion to the right hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It may be you would bring it into two files.</p>
            <p>Then you may giue the word of direction thus,
<q>Rankes file to the right hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or,
<q>Rankes file by Conuerſion to the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> left hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is thus performed.</p>
            <p>Halfe the rankes falls backe into the ſpaces behinde the right hand men of the right<note n="a" place="margin">The right hand file pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes the right flanke.</note> flanke,<note n="b" place="margin">The left hand file precedes the left flanke.</note> and the other halfe into the ſpaces behinde the left hand men of the left Flanke, doing that by diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb facs="tcp:9112:39"/> which the former did intire by this word of Command, <hi>(Rankes file to the right)</hi> but you muſt obſerue a double diſtance betweene Ranke and Ranke, to doe it, or it cannot be well done. We haue another way to doe the former (which is) by drawing or leading forth of Rankes, this is (as the other) new and vpſtart. We haue another way (by leading forth of files) priſtine or anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, commonly vſed in former times both of <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xenophon Cyrop.</hi> l. 2. 56.</note>You ſhall reade of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the elder, how he commanded thirtie thouſand men to be drawne forth (out of<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>A Phalange is a groſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of men brought into a battell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Xenophon</hi> in his 4. booke of the aſcent of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the younger.</p>
               </note> a Phalange) into a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle file. And it was his cuſtome when euer his ſouldiers went to dinner, to bring them forth file by file, and into a Phalange or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againe at the ſound of a horne or a word giuen.</p>
            <p>You ſhall reade of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that when they were to aſcend the <hi>Colchian</hi> Mountaines, they put themſelues into ſeuerall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and euery company into a ſingle file, euery file hauing an hundred men a peece, reducing againe into a body when they came to the top of them, where was roome enough. This the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> at that time did doe. Which we Command thus.</p>
            <q>Right hand file leade forth, the reſt follow in ſequence one behinde another.</q>
            <p>Thus many wayes, may the Depth be doubled by Number, to alter or change the forme of a battell.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that there are many more waies to doe it.</p>
            <p>For in the Artillery garden, this word of Command is frequent. <hi>(Aduance your files to the right hand)</hi> which is the doubling of the Depth. One file aduances to ſtand before another, the ſecond before the firſt, the fourth before the third, or the contrary as the word is giuen.</p>
            <p>This is the way to doe it, and I will name no more.</p>
            <p>All this variety of waies helpes ſuch as would be exquiſite in exerciſing. I ſay would; are not already. I preſume not to teach any that knowes more then my ſelfe; Nor ſuch as knowes leſſe then my ſelfe, yet ſcornes to be taught: but ſuch as knowes little (it may be nothing) yet haue a a deſire to learne; To ſuch, I that know ſome thing, (to others but little) doe impart that little which I haue. And in the next chapter will teach them how to exerciſe a company as I my ſelfe haue beene taught in the Artilery Garden, or elſewhere, for I haue attained nothing but by paines taking, much coſt, and reading.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9112:39"/>
            <p>But firſt obſerue my Method in Exerciſing.</p>
            <p>My Method in Exerciſing, is not at this time to Intermeddle with new formes of battells, various fights, ſundry kindes of Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and the like; But to apply my ſelfe ſomewhat to that which hath been deliuered, practized in former times, agreeing with our moderne diſcipline, and at this time in vſe, beginning at the firſt principle of all, to order a company of men into a battell that are at firſt confuſed one among another, and to doe it by diſtinct words of Command, whereby they may order themſelues into a body, without helpe of a Sergeant, taking their firſt diſtance of ſix foot in ſquare both in file and ranke, in which we commonly vſe at the firſt to exerciſe our Motions in. All this I meane to doe, and the Chapter following will ſhew it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> This Chapter ſheweth a young Commander how he ſhould begin to order his Company: How to command the ſame properly by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall diſtinct words of Command: And to obſerue true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in euery Motion: Whether it be to Face, to Wheele, to Charge, to Counter-march, or double.</head>
            <p>THus then he may Command (when the Company is vnorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, intermingled one with another, parted from their Armes, and lying in ſundry places.)</p>
            <list>
               <item>Separate your ſelues.</item>
               <item>To your Armes.</item>
               <item>File and Ranke your ſelues.</item>
               <item>Euery File-leader, know his place.</item>
               <item>Aduance your Pikes.</item>
               <item>Shoulder your Muskets.</item>
               <item>Fall into a body, and flanke your Pikes with Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets.</item>
               <item>Take your firſt diſtance ſix foot both in File and Ranke.</item>
               <item>Order your Pikes.</item>
               <item>Reſt your Muskets.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:40"/>
               <item>Stand Right in your Files.</item>
               <item>Stand right in your Rankes.</item>
               <item>Marke your Directions. Silence.</item>
               <item>Face to the right hand. as you were.</item>
               <item>Face to the left hand. as you were.</item>
               <item>Face to the right hand about. as you were.</item>
               <item>Face to the left hand about. as you were.</item>
               <item>Rankes to the right hand double. as you were.</item>
               <item>Rankes to the left hand double. as you were.</item>
               <item>Files to the right hand double. as you were.</item>
               <item>Files to the left hand double. as you were.</item>
               <item>Middle men to the right hand, Double your Front. Middle men as you were.</item>
               <item>Middle men to the left hand, Double your Front. Middle men as you were.</item>
               <item>Middle men to the right hand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, Double your Front. Middle men as you were.</item>
               <item>Middle men to the left hand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, Double your Front. Middle men as you were.</item>
               <item>Middle men double your Front to the right and left hand by diuiſion.</item>
               <item>Middle men as you were.</item>
               <item>Bringers vp to the right hand, Double your Front. Bringers vp as you were.</item>
               <item>Bringers vp to the left hand, Double your Front. Bringers vp as you were.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Now they muſt aduance their Pikes, and ſo Counter-march.</note>Rankes to the right hand Counter-march.</item>
               <item>Rankes to the left hand Counter-march.</item>
               <item>Files to the right hand Counter-march.</item>
               <item>Files to the left hand Counter-march.</item>
               <item>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">The ſecond Diſtance is for Wheeling and charging.</note>Files cloſe to your Order. Three foot in File and Ranke.</item>
               <item>Rankes cloſe to your Order. Three foot in File and Ranke.</item>
               <item>Wheele to the right hand.</item>
               <item>Wheele to the left hand.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Charging vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtand, when their Pikes are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced.</note>Wheele to the right hand about.</item>
               <item>Wheele to the left hand about.</item>
               <item>Charge to the right hand. As you were.</item>
               <item>Charge to the left hand. As you were.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Charge to both by diuiſion, As you were.</item>
               <item>Charge to the Front, As you were.</item>
               <item>Charge to the Reare, As you were.</item>
               <item>Charge to both by diuiſion, As you were.</item>
               <item>Charge, Front, Reare, and Flankes, As you were.</item>
               <item>Open y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Files to your open Order. Six foot.</item>
               <item>Open your Rankes to your open Order. Six foot.</item>
               <item>Order your Pikes. March.</item>
               <item>Shoulder your Pikes. March.</item>
               <item>Charge to the right hand.<note place="margin">Marching and charging from the ſhoulder, at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As you were. March. <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Charge to the left hand. <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As you were. March. <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Charge to the Reare. <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As you were. March. <hi>Do all this by the beat of the Drumme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beare-vp your Pikes and Counter-march to the right hand.<note place="margin">This was done by Captaine <hi>Bingham</hi> in the Artillery Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note>
               </item>
               <item>Beare-vp your Pikes, and Counter-march to the left hand.</item>
               <item>Aduance your Pikes marching. <hi>Keepe your firſt Diſtance ſix foot in File &amp; Ranke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Port your Pikes marching. <hi>Keepe your firſt Diſtance ſix foot in File &amp; Ranke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Traile your Pikes marching. <hi>Keepe your firſt Diſtance ſix foot in File &amp; Ranke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cheeke your Pikes from the traile. <hi>Keepe your firſt Diſtance ſix foot in File &amp; Ranke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Make a ſtand: Marke your Directions.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The right hand file lead forth, the reſt follow in ſequence one after another.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Lay your Pikes on the outſide one of another.</item>
               <item>Recouer (Marching) and aduance your Pikes. Stand.</item>
               <item>File-leaders bring vp your Files into a body.</item>
               <item>Files open to the right hand Open order. Six foot.</item>
               <item>Files cloſe to the left hand to your Order. Three foot.</item>
               <item>To the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>A foot and a halfe. In F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le.</item>
               <item>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkes open backward to your double Diſtance. Twelue foot.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:9112:41"/>
               <item>Rankes File to the right hand. Rankes as you were.</item>
               <item>Rankes File to the left hand. Rankes as you were.</item>
               <item>Rankes File to the right and left hand.</item>
               <item>Cloſe your Rankes to ſix foot.</item>
               <item>Open your Files to ſix foot.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Being reduced to your firſt Diſtance.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Order your Pikes.</item>
               <item>Lay downe your Pikes.</item>
               <item>Take vp your Pikes, and order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus much for Exerciſing, and of the Poſtures of the Pike therein vſed. The ſeuerall Poſtures of the Musket followeth in the next Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> Of the Poſtures of the Musket.</head>
            <p>THe Poſtures of the Musket are ſundry and many. Some make 32. ſome 40. ſome 43. ſome more, ſome leſſe. All which are for Military inſtruction in the time of Trayning, and to make the Souldier moſt exquiſite and perfect: But in time of preſent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice before the face of the enemy, or in fight, then all this great number of Poſtures they reduce into three only and no more, viz.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Make ready.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Giue fire.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> All the other, they wittily and properly ſort into foure kindes, or orders: To be performed, <hi>Standing, Marching, Charging,</hi> and <hi>Diſcharging;</hi> (as is to be ſeene in Captaine <hi>Pantons</hi> Table,) all which muſt be obſerued. Thus much of them.</p>
            <p>The Poſtures or words of Command which we muſt vſe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Training, or daily exerciſing of Souldiers, agreeing to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> forme, (and by order from his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuy Councell) are theſe:
<list>
                  <item>March with your Musket ſhouldred, and the Reſt in your right hand.</item>
                  <item>March, and with the Musket carry the Reſt.</item>
                  <item>Sinke your Reſt, and vnſhoulder your Musket.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9112:41"/>
                  <item>Poyſe it in your right hand, and let it ſinke into the left.</item>
                  <item>In your left hand hold your Musket, and carry your Reſt with it.</item>
                  <item>Take your Match in the right hand betweene the ſecond fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thombe.</item>
                  <item>Hold your Match faſt and blow your coale:</item>
                  <item>Cocke your Match.</item>
                  <item>Try your Match.</item>
                  <item>Guard your pan and blow your match.</item>
                  <item>Open your pan.</item>
                  <item>Preſent.</item>
                  <item>Giue fire.</item>
                  <item>Diſmount your Musket and carry it with your Reſt.</item>
                  <item>Vncocke your match, and returne it betweene your fingers.</item>
                  <item>Cleare your pan.</item>
                  <item>Prime your pan.</item>
                  <item>Shut your pan.</item>
                  <item>Caſt off your looſe powder.</item>
                  <item>Blow your pan.</item>
                  <item>Caſt about your Musket.</item>
                  <item>Traile your Reſt.</item>
                  <item>Open your charge.</item>
                  <item>Charge with powder.</item>
                  <item>Draw out your ſcowring ſticke.</item>
                  <item>Shorten your ſticke.</item>
                  <item>Ramme in your powder.</item>
                  <item>Draw out your ſticke.</item>
                  <item>Charge with Bullet.</item>
                  <item>Ramme in your Bullet.</item>
                  <item>Draw out your ſticke.</item>
                  <item>Shorten your ſticke and put it vp.</item>
                  <item>Bring your Musket forward with your left hand.</item>
                  <item>Poyſe it in your right hand and recouer your Reſt.</item>
                  <item>Shoulder your Musket.</item>
                  <item>March and carry your Reſt with your Musket.</item>
                  <item>Vnſhoulder your Musket.</item>
                  <item>Lay your Musket in the Reſt.</item>
                  <item>Stand Reſted.</item>
                  <item>Your ſaluting Poſture,] as you were.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9112:42"/>
                  <item>In the right hand take your Match betweene the ſecond finger and the thumbe.</item>
                  <item>Blow your Match.</item>
                  <item>Cocke your Match.</item>
                  <item>Try your Match.</item>
                  <item>Guard your pan and be ready.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt is the Sentinell Poſture.</p>
            <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s I haue run ouer the Poſtures of the Musket, after the Low Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, firſt marching, then diſcharging, then c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging, after ſtanding. Adding three more vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them, (becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with the bullet was left out:) which I hope will giue oftence to none.</p>
            <p>As for the geſture of the body, hand and foot, to grace the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, I referre you to the booke expreſſing it by Figures; Or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tillery Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den, or Military Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd, where it is done by ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>y: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuer to be obtained without practiſe. You may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egin whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you pleaſe, for this forme is not ſo ſtrictly ob er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Artillery Garden.</p>
            <p>B ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou had the Poſtures of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke implicite, and not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> but mixt with other kindes of Motions different from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m; I will in the next Chapter ſhew them ſeuerall, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Of the ſeuerall Poſtures of the Pike.</head>
            <p>THe ſeuerall Poſtures of the Pike (ſaith Sargeant <hi>Truſſell</hi>) are in number twelue. Three are to be done ſtanding, ſix marching, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d three charging.</p>
            <p>The three which are to be done ſtanding he expreſſeth thus:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lay d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vp y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>der your Pik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which are to be done Marching he expreſſeth thus
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ance your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9112:42"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Shoulder your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leuell your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Slope your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cheeke your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Traile your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The three which are to be done charging he expreſſeth thus:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charge ouer hand.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charge at the right foot for Horſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This is the briefe Epitome of the Poſtures which that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tooke from Captaine <hi>Pantons</hi> Table: Captaine <hi>Panton</hi> from the Booke publiſhed by the moſt Excellent Prince, the Count <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and I from both. So I end my Booke. Let God haue the glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exodus 15 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The <hi>LORD</hi> is a man of Warre: His name is <hi>IEHOVAH.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
